听译/校对/时间轴：普赖尔蒂斯@豆瓣
1880年代末起
since the late 1880s
视觉艺术家和讲故事的人
visual artist and story-tellers
开始使用活动影像来创造神奇的世界
have used moving images to create amazing worlds
电影给我们启示
movies have inspired us
激励我们并捕获我们的想象
thrilled us and capture our imaginations
胶片，曾帮助我们分享经验和梦想
film, has helped us to share our experiences and dreams
100年来，化学胶片曾经是
photo chemical film, has been the exclusive format
捕获、冲显、放映和储存动态影像
capture, develop, project and store moving images
的唯一格式
for over 100 years
近些年才发展起一种新技术
it was only resently that a new technology had immerged
正挑战着胶片所代表的影像质量和工作流程的黄金地位
that challenging film place of gold standards for quality and workflow
数字技术已经进化到可以替代胶片
digital technology is evolving to a point that
执行最主要的任务：
means very well replace film as the prirary mean
创造和分享动态影像
of creating and sharing motion pictures
这部记录作品叫《side by side》
the documentary doing is called side by side
涉及到数字电影的科学、艺术和影响
it's the documentary about science, art and impact of digital cinema
一百年的化学胶片发展
100 years of photo chemical film making
目前已经到达了一个临界状态
right now it reached a kind of threshold of tipping point
这场对话，这个时间点
in this conversaton, in this intersection of time
是历史性的
is historic
我们怕是已经来到了
we've kind of come to this place where
胶片的末日
it is the end of film
我们今在何方
where are we today
这很令人兴奋，因为这是重新创造的新媒介
it's exciting, because it's a re-invention of new medium
如果化学摄影法可以承载我们文化中的美德
if the photo chemical process has virtues through our culture
另一形式有何不可？
why aren't you another level
关键是你怎么用它讲故事
how do you use it to tell a story
怎么用它去描绘一个场景
how do you use it to paint apicture
您算和胶片一刀两断了吗？
are you done with film
不要故意带我，基努
don’t hold me to it, Keanu
不过
but…
我想是的
I think I am
数字摄影机是电影业的新美学手段
digital cameras are the new aesthetic that coming to cinema
同时我们又哀悼胶片的衰落
and at the same time we are going to mourn the loss of film
我清楚知道在哪、为什么要用胶片拍电影
I am costly(?) to justify where and why I shoot a film by film
不过实话说我没听说过谁知道为啥一定要用数字拍电影
But I don’t hear anybody being honestly to justify why they want to shoot a film digitally
我希望我所想象的一切都能真实展示
I want everything I could imagine to be something we can realize
不过胶片很难实现这一点
I saw the door opening on a field of possibility that you just couldn’t do it with film
如今比较悲哀的是
It’s really sad right now
摄影开始批量使用数码技术
to see cameras cording imagery a serial way
取代胶片
starting to take over film
胶片拍摄
我才不要把油画换成蜡笔画（画面质感）
I’m not gonna trade my oil paintings to seta crayons
数字拍摄
有人看好数字技术
there will be people who will chip in digital
也有人不仅想杀掉这只生金蛋的鹅
there will be people who will not only kill the goose lay the golden egg
还要在之前把它搞的一团糟
they’ll sort of mess it first
如果数字技术取代胶片
if the intention of that digital will replace film
恰恰是因为我们所讨厌它的一些方面，那很悲哀
I’ll be sad if it's doing acturally exactly where we hate it
因为数字能够做的胶片效果胶片自然可以做到更好
because that digital now can make it look like film that film is inherently better
就因为我们喜欢这种更好的感觉
just we like the way it looks better
（就否定数字技术）这有点专断
which seems kind of arbitrary that we were used to
胶片是19世纪的发明
film is a 19th century invention
我们已经到达了化学照相法的顶峰
we are on the top of photo chemical process
很难再有进步
this is about as far as ever we can go
数字技术发展至今
digital is here now
还有很长的路要走
but it’s gonna keep going
你会是数字发展的参与者
and you’re gonna be part of that
参与者将决定数字技术的未来
who’s be gonna be a part of that dictating where that goes
我觉得胶片不会怎样
I don’t think films going anywhere
我觉得完全摒弃胶片无论对人还是影片画面都不能
I don’t think it’s to the image or anybody to totally eliminate film
会有很多人加入我们，为胶片而战
there gonna be many of us, they’ll fight for film
为在感光剂上摄影的经验而战
fight for the experience of shooting on emulsion
我们处于某种变革的迷雾中
we really are in the mist of some sort of revolution
这种变革威胁到影片的基本质量
that threatens the status qual
所以这既是可怕的又是自由的
it’s so potentially either scary thing or very liberating thing
阴阳相成
电影制作第一步：
one of the first steps of production process
捕获影像
is capturing the images in camera
导演、演员、摄像师和全体制作组
the director, actors, cinematographer and the entire production team
共同努力把剧本变活
work together to bring the script to life
摄像技师，也叫摄影指导或DP
the cinematographer, also called the director of photography or DP
帮助导演达成电影的影像效果
helps the director achieve the look of the movie
DP的职责在于决定摄影装备
the DP is responsible for knowing what equipment is needed
以及了解其摄影原理
and how it works in order to capture the scenes
摄影指导要注意颜色和构图
a director of photography looks at color and composition
大卫 芬奇 导演
（社交网络/搏击会/七宗罪）
以及角度和其它构成电影的元素
and angles and all those things in terms of how the movie is being built
光照到皮肤的效果，光穿过头发的效果
the quality of light of skin, the quality of light through hair,
光透过窗户再从地板反射的效果
the quality of light through the window and bouncing off the floor
这些都要等同真实世界的构造
they’re equating the building of this world
和真实世界的
and terms of energy
能量反射效果
that reflects off objects
问题是
the question is about
构图，情感，怎么去让人感觉
framing, sensibility, how to make people feel
迈克尔 查普曼，摄影
（出租车司机/愤怒的公牛/粗野少年）
把情绪付诸光线
bringing emotion into the lights
基于要恰当的处理光线
comes from being appropriate and somehow being
不过最棒的是要高于“恰当”
the really great is, more than appropriate
真正让人惊奇的是
they really startle you with how wonderfully
我能如何漂亮的展现所有动作
I could have this look is on whatever they’re doing
出租车司机，1976
这种专业技术水平上
That level of crossmanship? or technical expertise
约翰 马西森，摄影
（角斗士/浪人47/X战警：第一战）
你没法解释自己要做什么
You can’t explain what you’re gonna do
所以他们必须把你当回事
so there is a certain matter of leap of faith that they have to having you
现代启示录，1979
维托里奥 斯托拉罗，摄影
（现代启示录/末代皇帝/小活佛）
作为摄影师
To be a cinematographer
要有艺术方面的知识
is to have the knowledge of the art
毫无疑问，电影是一种利用科技实现的综合艺术
Without any doubt, cinema today is a mix of art in technology
大卫 斯坦普，视觉特效
（X战警，X战警2，火星人玩转地球）
如今在这个领域还要懂点技术才行
Today, in this area, you also have to be a bit of technician
你得懂设备
You have to know the equipment
明白成像流程的所有环节对DP来说非常重要
It’s really important for DP to understand the entire links of the image chain
从获取到开掘
From acquisition to excavation
摄像机是测量光子并使其聚焦
The camera is a tool that focuses and measures
并以图片形式将其记录的工具
Photons of light and record them in images
通过胶片摄像机
With a film camera
光透过镜头并照射到电影胶片上
Light enter through the lens and hits the frame film behind the lens
胶片表面覆有含卤化银晶体颗粒的乳剂
The film is covered emulsion that contain grains of silver halides crystals
这些晶体在光照下会发生化学反应
These crystals react chemically when light hits them
显影时晶体会转化为金属银
And the crystal change to silver metal when they are developed
这样拍摄的影像就在胶片上形成了
A photograph image is formed on the film
瑞德 穆拉诺，摄影
（冰冻之河/小小鸟/为了艾伦）
对于胶片的质感和颗粒感
There is something about the texture of the grain structure of film
我个人会调整直到觉得舒服
That personally I hold on till it’s like a comforting thing to me
这种感觉更像是可触的
And it feels more tangible
我打开并轻击它们的时候很有质感
How I open up and flip themselves give sort of touch of quality
布拉德福德 杨，摄影
（作品都是没听过的独立制作，就不翻了…）
这种图片的颗粒感
Still have some granularity in the image that
可以让强光生动
keeps high light living and keeps blacks
并赋予暗光更多微妙特性
with a little bit more nuance characters in them
迪克 蒲伯，摄影
（秘密与谎言/魔术师/无忧无虑）
我热爱颗粒感和纹理
I greaten grain and texture
它们能给你多种多样的选择
they give you a variety of different opportunities
魔术师，2006
胶片拍摄的基本流程
The workflow on the film set
就是你要带上几千尺的胶片
Basically means that you take thousand-foot load of film
装到胶卷盒里
loaded in to the magazines
每卷也就够你拍个10分钟多点
And that enable you to shoot for roughly 10+ minutes per roll of film
接着是休息时间
And it gives a natural break of action
这时候有人把拍满的胶卷拽出来
when someone pulls the magazine off the camera
再把新胶卷放进去
And put a new magazine on
接着这些胶片会被送到胶片实验室
Then the film goes away to the film lab
过夜显影
And it developed over night
然后冲印
And printed
第二天样片出炉
And in the next day, you could see dailys
有好多年这都是一件乐事
There was a joy for many many years
珊迪 希瑟，摄影
（拜见布朗一家/早安孟买/阶梯下的恶魔）
因为我们是片场幽灵
For us to be the genes on set
所以我们热爱样片
That’s why we like dailys
我们都去表演，我们喜欢这样
We’d all go, we’d act, we’d like
我们爱干嘛干嘛，也喜欢我们干的事
We’d do all we do, and we’d love what we did
接着每个人都入了迷
and then everybody would rapt
然后第二天一早我们回实验室的时候
and the next morning we came back in the lab
我们都惊呼：看看我们都干了些什么
We went “wow, look what we got.”
这真是神奇
You know it was magic
唐纳 麦卡派恩，摄影
（金刚狼/红磨坊/铁血战士）
摄影指导是魔术师
The director of photography was a magician
他是唯一真正可能知道
He was the only? one who actually, probably knew
第二天样片会怎么样的人
what’s gonna beyond the screen the next day
这给了你不少权利和伙伴
And this gets you a lot of authority and pal
拍摄的时候你得有种鉴定的信念
There is a certain believe of faith you take when you shoot the film
这很浪漫的
And there are something really romantic about that
样片回来每个人都兴冲冲想看看你拍了些什么
Get your dailys back and everyone being really excited to see what you got
我不喜欢被样片背叛
I don’t like the betrayal of dailys
我不喜欢去全神贯注的看表演时候
I don’t like going in and seeing and getting swept up with the performance
在25尺的屏幕上发现拍摄失焦了
And then seeing go out focus on 25-foot screen
而且还知道这重来不了
and knowing that there’s no way to retrieve that
罗伯特 罗德里格兹，导演/摄影
（罪恶之城/非常小特务/墨西哥往事）
拍电影的时候有种感觉
But in like a film about that feeling
过了半天一天
midway to the day, end of the day
真的拍了什么东西吗？我想不起来我拍了点啥
did we get anything, that day? I didn’t remember, I didn’t get it
因为你看不见所以没有拍过的痕迹
Didn’t feel we put the flag in it cause you couldn’t see
就像关了灯画画
it’s like painting with the lights off
但是DP会告诉你：
But the DP will tell you:
没啊，灯没关，都在我脑子里呢
it’s not, the lights aren’t off, it’s in my head
在他脑子里，这不错
It’s in his head, well that’s great
但扛摄像机的不是我
but I’m off bringing the camera
选镜头的也不是我，我就管表演怎么样
picking the lenses, I’m judging the performances
数位摄像机不使用胶片
A digital camera does not use film
相对的，镜头后是电子传感器或芯片
Instead, it has an electronic sensor or chip behind the lens
传感器由许多微小的图像元素构成
The sensor, is made up with millions of tiny picture elements
或简称像素
or pixels for short
当光进入摄像机的时候
when light enters the camera
击打像素并产生各自独立的电子电荷
it hit the pixels and create individual electronic charges
这些电荷被放大后转化为代表图像的数位信息
these charges are magnifying converted into digital data that represent the image
大卫 塔特肖，摄影
（星球大战1-3/极速赛车手/绿里奇迹）
用胶片拍摄由于它一直在转
ring the film that it just constantly moving
所以总有点模糊
So the result is kind of fuzziness
而像素这样的东西
well the pixel kind
是非常细致精确的
is very fine-line, accurate, exact thing
用带显示器的数位摄像机
with digital cameras in monitors
你能在拍摄的同时观看拍下的东西
you are able to see exactly what you are recording on sight as you’re shooting
不同于胶片摄像机
unlike film cameras
你不用等上一天才能看自己拍了些什么
you don’t have to wait a day to see what you’ve captured
样片不再是“隔天的”
they’re no longer dailys
而是“即取的”
they are “immediatelys”
费尔 麦休克斯
（皇家赌场/佐罗传奇/蓝精灵）
你坐在片场或帐篷什么的地方
You sit round back of the set or in the tent somewhere
看着巨型显示器
looking at the huge monitor
然后通过这个作调整
and make adjustment from that
这和现场调整没什么两样
which is actually quite alike
因为你看到画面就是现场
because that means you seeing the picture exactly it is
用胶片的话，一个拍摄
And with old film, a capture
要过夜才能看，而且有时会担心
it was overnight and sometime you got the burden
我是不是拍的没问题
that “I wonder if I go there right”
(?)我认为不管样片有多好都得有个后备措施
(?)I think we need more backine and don’t worry how great daily is
乔治 卢卡斯，导演/制片人
（星球大战1-4/500年后/美国风情画）
谁都知道看样片怎么回事
They know as well as anybody that you go to dailys
不过我真觉得应该有更多后备措施
and I really think there should be more backline in there
你要是在片场干过
But If you do it on the set
就知道后备措施的重要性了
You can understand it, more backlines
（数位摄像）实现了这点，这很好，就是我想要的
And they do it, it’s ok cause that is exactly what I want
因为在电影院放出来也是这样
cause it exactly is the way could be in the movie theater
人们都这么说：
People speak about:
谢天谢地，我能看见我正在拍的东西
thank god, I can see what I’m getting on
我不用等到明天早上了
I don’t have to wait until tomorrow
我能更专注，我知道我在拍什么
I can see it and focus on it I know what I’m getting
克里斯托弗 诺兰，导演
（黑暗骑士/盗梦空间/记忆碎片）
在片场看显示器
few watching the monitor on set
你觉得你真的看到你拍的东西了
and you feel that you really seeing what you’ve got
其实这种想法欺骗了你
this thinking is fooling yourself
你的观众是要在1000倍大的屏幕上看这些东西
Your audience are gonna watch the film on the screen is 1000 times bigger
你只是在大电视上看
you watch it on large TV
没错，你能看见自己拍了什么，就在那
Yes, you see what you get it, that’s right there
马丁 斯科塞斯，导演
纽约黑帮/出租车司/机好家伙
我的经验建议之后再看拍的东西
Proof for me that I think you need to see rushes later
我认为这是集中精力的方法
I think it’s concentrate
表演或仅仅是动作
But the performances or just the movement
你可以在特定的时间去看
that is something you can see in a special time
摄制电影的过程是摄影指导的技术和秘密
The process of shooting film was the DP’s art and secret
查理 何兹费得，特艺彩色纽约市场部高级副总裁
现在摄影师只是数位摄影前面的显示器
Today the cinematographer is a monitor on the digital shoot
他们拍什么都能被看见，并任人评判
and everything they are doing could seen, criticized and questioned
有时这挺让人分心的
It’s very distractive sometimes
乔 舒马赫，导演
（永远的蝙蝠侠/电话亭/粗野少年）
我和几个演员一起工作
I work with a couple of actors
每天坚持和其中某一个看（样片）
that insist on I’m look at it everyday with one of the actors
我可以边看边说
I was able to talk among of it
因为这能让他的表演变得非常自信
because it’s making his performances very self-conscious
是吗？
Right?
你是不是听说他们都只看他们的头发而已？
Are you also convinced that everybody is just looking at their hair?
作为摄影师最大乐趣之一
One of the great pleasure that being a cameraman was
那些尊崇制片人意愿的人
that the people who was the suits on the producer
他们都觉得自己知道怎么表演
They all think they know how to act
他们都觉得自己知道怎么写剧本
they all think they know how to write
他们都觉得自己知道怎么导演
they all think they know how to direct
但是他们都知道自己不会摄像
But they knew they didn’t knew how to shoot
这完全取决于你
So I say this is really got on you
你可以说：看吧，这片子是你做的
you could say: here, this the media you do it
我才是魔术师
I was the charmer
不过现在会摄像是另一码事了
But now, being a thing that you can shoot is not like it used to be
有些摄像师之所以当摄像师
There’re cinematographers who became cinematographers
是因为他们热爱摄像的魔力
because they love the voodoo of it
他们喜欢导演对他们说：
They love it when the director said to them:
“那个角落
“down that cornor”
你能看见吗？好像要消失了”
will you able to that? that’s kind of melt away”
他们倒是机灵：“明天看嘛，肯定超惊喜，包你满意”
they get to guile: “ just wait till tomorrow, it’s gonna be amazing, you’re gonna love it.”
七宗罪，1995
接下来，我经历过的，他们把样片搞定了，我就会…
and then, I had this experience, they’ve set the dailys then I’ve gone
比如《七宗罪》里有些令人兴奋的东西就是表现不出来
some of the durance can’t just work on se7en you just go "wow"
不过倒是有个差不多的人在，所以你就会
but there is the an equal man on time so you go:
看着它说：“这他妈怎么回事？”
look at it and say: “what the fuck?”
现在有了数位摄像机
Now with digital cameras
人人都能看见拍摄的结果
everyone could see exactly what things were going to look like
这改变了你从前对摄像的喜爱方式
that changes the way you like it
甚至改变了你的表演
it may even change your performance
因为这给拍电影带来了完全不同的感受
Because it creates a different feelings in the whole thing
这让我们的创造性有了更多空间
It gives us more scope to be creative
这点令人兴奋
That was exciting
杰夫 波尔， 摄影
（街头霸王：春丽传/变异编年史/黑暗乡村）
对我来说这就是数位摄像机革命的全部
That for me it’s digital revolution of cameras all about
贝尔实验室 出品
1969年，在位于新泽西的贝尔实验室
In 1969, at bell labs in New Jersey
乔治史密斯和威乐鲍尔
George Smith and Willard Boyle
提出电荷藕合装置（CCD）构想
came up with the idea for the charged couple device
两位老爷子因此获得2009年诺贝尔物理学奖
并发明了第一个CCD芯片
and the first CCD chip was created
CCD的特点之一是
One of the things that makes the CCD unique
它可以执行某些特殊功能
is its ability to performs specialized functions
例如当摄像机用
such as acting as a camera
你所看到的我们在电视上的图像
The image that you see on the TV screen aboout of us
就是在我们前方的这个小CCD摄像机拍摄的
is being produced by the small CCD camera which is directly in front of us here
70年代早期，在参观贝尔实验室后
In the early 1970s, after a visit to bell labs
索尼公司开始应用CCD技术推广并发展新产品
SONY started investing in and developing products using the CCD technology
盛田昭夫是索尼之父
Akio Morita was the father of SONY
阿列克 沙匹罗，索尼市场部高级副总裁
他是好莱坞的拥簇
He was always an amor of Hollywood
而设计电子摄像机是他的梦想
And it was his dream to design an electronic camera
能创造和35mm胶片同等或更佳质量的图像
That could create images were equaling or better than the 35mm film
广告：随时随地，想拍就拍
record what you want , when you want
80年代中期
In the mid of 1980s
索尼生产了第一批消费型CCD便携式摄像机
SONY was producing its first consumer quality CCD camcorders
哥本哈根，丹麦
90年代
In the 1990s
小型标清摄像机开始用于数位拍摄
small standard definition cameras began recording digitally
它们开始用于电影拍摄
They were first to use cinematically
始于在丹麦兴起的“道格玛95”运动
when they were embraced by the dogma 95 movement in Denmark
您能不能谈谈
Can you speak a little bit about
您是什么时候开始使用数位…
Where did you first coming to digital…
拉斯 冯 提尔，导演
（抑郁症/反基督者/黑暗中的舞者）
实际上是偶然
Actually it’s by chance
因为我们搞了个“道格玛95”
Because we made this thing called dogma 95
而且制定了一些规则
And we made up some rules
其中一条是
And one of them was that
必须使用35mm拍摄
the thing has to be filmed by academy 35mm
接着另一条又说
And on e of them said
必须是手持摄像机
it had to be hand-held camera also
然后我提议，既然如此
And then I said, if that is the case
我们也能用录像
we can also use video
那时候又正好这些摄像机问世了
And that was just at the same time that these cameras came to appear
安东尼 多德 曼妥是第一个拍摄“道格玛95”的DP
Anthony Dod Mantle was the DP who shot the first dogma film
由托马斯 温特伯格执导的《家宴》
Thomas Winterberg‘s  celebration
(?)用数位拍摄还能保证电影的纯粹性吗？
(?)Was it pure also of digital video？
摄像机比较轻，这么点重量不足以…
The lightness of the camera, the weight that you couldn’t…
我第一次用这个是这样的：
I tell you it was the first hit me
我去哥本哈根的农贸市场
I was coming up the food market in Copenhagen
安东尼 多德 曼妥，摄影
（家宴/惊变28天/贫民窟的百万富翁）
我有台索尼PC3，就是我拍《家宴》的那一台
I had a SONY PC 3 and that’s the exact camera I end shooting celebration
我记起生机勃勃的拥挤场景
and I remember scenes crowd with lives
假设我们穿过这样工业化背景的地方
Supported us just moving across this field with a industrial backdrop
有雾，模糊，这种感觉很哥特
Into mist and hazing, it’s gothic
我才开始学习怎么用它
I was just learning how to play with it
到处拍，对这小东西有种怪怪的感觉
Swept it around and I got this weird moment of this midgetcy
又轻又小
Of lightness and midgetcy
而当我看到画面时又颇感震惊
and I looked at the image and said “my god”
这可以是很好的摄像机
and that’s gonna be nice cameras
我认为
I called that
家宴，1998
用微型摄像机拍摄《家宴》有很多话可说
Too much say when I was shooting in celebration on the small cameras
因为我想成为《家宴》的主角
Casuse I want to be a protagonist on celebration
电影的构成实际上就是摄像机充满情绪化的移动
The combination of the movie is actually emotional movements of the camera
这决定了电影的视角
which probably defined that film’s visual line
应该把它与演员的表演
should depart them from the actors
和剧本的指导分离开
and the watching great script
用这台摄像机，这些问题迎刃而解
with that camera and I suddenly solve these smooth
这种移动方式是从前的摄影经验里没有的
it’s possible movements I didn’t know in my cinema
而这变成了我对《家宴》的贡献
And that became my donation for  celebration
《家宴》意味着什么
What  celebration meant
其它这个领域的电影又意味着什么
and what a lot of the other films at that area meant?
白痴，1998
是不是要完全重新思考电影制作的技术层面了呢
Was that you just have to completely rethink the technical side of the film making
敏郎悲歌，1999
这些电影让人完全可以为了创意而创作
they brought people to film making for creativities sake
驴孩朱丽安，1999
国王不死，2000
这些电影证明电影制作原理只是为创意服务而已
They pointed out that the mechanism of film making only serves creative
查克和贝克，2000
用DV拍摄
With DV
杰森 科略特，制片
（查克和贝克/咖啡与香烟/夺命手术）
都是为了…
Came this whole idea of
等等
wait a second
要是我们能降低预算
if we lower our budgets
作为导演和制片人来说就能有更大的自由度
we get more freedom as directors and producers
用DV拍电影意味着这就是一坨屎
Shooting a film on video of that point meant it was crap
乔弗利 吉尔莫，电影节导演
（翠贝卡电影节/圣丹斯电影节）
这基本上是个难以接受的事实
It was almost unaccepted truth
你并没有认真拍电影
that you didn’t shoot films
因为那是录像格式
that you’re serious about on any kind of video format
我们去那然后说：
We just started going out there and we are saying:
听着，我们要用数位拍摄
Look, we’re gonna make movie digitally
我们要做导演最终剪辑
we’re gonna give director’s final cut
全程尽在掌握
Totally create of control
不过我们会让这一切更省钱
But we’ll make them cheaper
我们的第一部电影是《查克和贝克》
And our very first movie was chuck and buck
你好啊贝克
Hey Buck
…好呀
uh, Hi
喝点啥吗？
can I get you something to drink?
不用，没事
oh, no, that’s alright
看回放会吓到自己
Looking at rushes it will scary yourself
冰糕要吗？
would you like some icecream?
真的吗，我爱冰糕耶
really? uh, I like icecream
天哪，看起来真够业余
Oh god, it looks so amateur
很多人其实…
A lot of people actually…
都是模仿
come it on hell modeled it looked
你特么想什么呢
what you’re thinking you fucking doing, man
我记得我们把它在圣丹斯上放映的情形
I remember when we presenting it on Sundance
可吓死他们了
they were scared to death
观影指南上写的就是这是拿DV拍的
The direction would be “this was shot on video”
这样的数位摄制作品作为
The digital presentation did not look nearly
胶片的替代品简直难以接受
at any way gonna be acceptable substitute of what film was
因为...毛片
Because of…porn
还有纪录片
And because of documentary
还有新闻报道
and because of news footage
小型摄像机视频让你觉得：
Video occupied the space in your mind like:
我在这，在这房间里，天，一切真的在发生
I’m here I’m in that room oh my god, this is really happening
而这让《查克和巴克》更好
And that makes chuck and buck better
艾伦 库拉斯，摄影
（迷途人生/暖暖内含光/大毒枭）
人们开始
People were starting to think
用完全不同的眼光去审视
in a completely different way about
技术和媒介
How could the technology and medium
如何帮助我们重新思考电影制作
help us to rethink film making
你发现人们开始挑战传统观念
You start to see people start to challenge the idea
迷途人生，2002
像InDigEnt（独立数位娱乐）这样的组织
as the group as InDigEnt (Independent Digital Entertainment )
他们制作标清视频
They were creating standard def video
然后用视频拼成电影再放出
That within they converted to film for seen actual released
盖瑞 文尼克，InDigEnt创始人（已故）
作为一个独立电影人
I think as a independent film maker
我认为我们正处于最令人兴奋的时代
we are at the most exciting time ever
因为现在我们能出去用DV拍摄电影
Because now we can go out and make a film on DV
蝌蚪，2002
奥斯卡交了新女友
Oscar has a new girlfriend
真的吗
really?
我们昨天好像讨论了很长时间这个话题了
it seems last day we get quite late for that conversation
有种想法是你要是用数位拍那就一定便宜
The idea was that if you shoot digitally it was cheap
所以彻底的帮助提升了电影制作的数量
And absolutely helped fill the number of movies that gotten make
我记得我在圣丹斯的头一年
I remember my first year on Sundance
在虚构作品类中我们遣返了35部提交作品
we return 35 submissions total of the fiction category
几年以后就翻了10倍
few years later it was 10 times of that
在圣诞斯电影节上
back to that Sundance days
有InDigEnt的作品，人们都觉得还好，毕竟是独立作品
the releases of InDigEnt, people were saying that’s ok for you as independent
卡罗林 卡普兰，制片
（蝌蚪/迷途人生/四月碎片）
不过这不是电影
But this isn’t cinema this isn’t…
这种说法很流行，用DV做电影再去圣丹斯
That was a huge saying to make film on a video camera and go to Sundance
我们因《迷途人生》赢得了最佳导演和最佳影片
And win best director, and win beat film for personal velocity
盖瑞自己的《蝌蚪》
Gary’s own film tadpole
就比较倾向于大众
And being sort of for normal man’s money
每个人都在努力：娱乐大众好赚钱
Everyone worked on it: make money from that sale
这就是大家都觉得用数位摄像没问题的时候
And that’s when a lot of the idea you can shoot film digitally
就像是对商品美学的品头论足
And it’s almost like a production aesthetic
争论开始了
And that’s when all those debates started
您一定知道
You must have heard that late 90s
90年代末电影的金标准和您使用的工具是什么呢
film’s gold standard and the tool you playing with are what?
贬低或推崇
debasing, fattening
我曾经受过打击…
I have been slapped around if you wanna…
“打击”是怎么回事
What do you mean “slapped around”？
(?)我被说成是个爆发基佬
(?)I mean I’ve been exploded and homosexualcated for the sentence
对我来说转投数位摄影是显然的
It was a quite obvious to me to go to digital
因为你可以熟练使用摄像机
because of mature you can have the camera
这种成熟程度显而易见
The amount of the mature you can have your camera was obvious
既然我决定用另一种工作方式创作
since I was trying to create another way of working with other tools
这点是比较重要的
And that was essential
大卫 林奇，导演
（蓝丝绒/象人/穆赫兰道）
为了拍长镜头
I imagine there was collaboration for you than
我猜您需要和演员密切合作是吗
terms of the relationship with your actors for longer takes？
是啊，基努
Yes you know, Keanu
10分钟到头了，其实根本没10分钟
10-minute is maximum, it wasn’t really 10
9分钟吧也就
9 or something
当那玩意儿开始转的时候
When that thing starts rolling
有种感觉
There’s kina underline feeling
宝贝开始转了
that precious stuff rolling through there
这让所有东西都紧张
And it puts kind of a tension on things
我想拍多长拍多长
Like a shoot as much as I wanted
我可以有最好的表演
I can get the best performances
我不用担心拍片是烧胶片
I didn’t have to worry about shooting is a little burst of film
这太荒谬了，不过我曾经就是这么担心的
That was ridiculous but that was what I had to do
相对来说曾经就是那么贵
that’s how expensive it was comparatively
数位摄影的话，一个小东西能拍40分钟
Digital, a little gizmo, 40 minutes
你能边拍
And you can be running this camera
边和演员讲话
and talking to the actor
再来也没问题
Starting over again
他们能够融入进去
And they get down in there
能抓拍以前的巨型设备
And catch a thing never would get caught
几乎从来没拍到过的东西
if you have the giant thing there
达内尔 马丁，导演
（冷门独立，不翻了…）
我喜欢用摄像机工作
I love to on the camera
尤其是到感情洋溢的地方，魔法就发生了
Especially when we were at the emotional place that magic is happening
你喊停的时候，突然间所有人都去那了
When you go cut, That all of a sudden everybody’s in there
而你就在那
And you were at a place where it is just there
接着万物静止
And then everything stops
接着是“好了，我们继续”
then “that’s ok, now go back to that”
而我说：“等等，要搞下摄像机，一分钟就好”
And I said “no, just went to the camera, back to one”
你要能够快归位
As fast as you can get back to your position
约翰 马尔科维奇，演员
（危险关系/太阳帝国/赤焰战场）
你还能再次离开
You can go again
我就是觉得等待的时间好多啊
I just thought there was way too much waiting
电影于我总有个动力问题
Because movies for me there is always momentum problem
因为我成长于剧院，那也是我接受表演训练的地方
Cause I grow up in the theater and that’s how I was trained
不过在拍电影的大多数时间我…
and a lot of time in movies I…
总有种感觉：“我们能走了么？”
feel like “can we go？”
对我来说连拍45分钟简直太难了
it‘s very tough for me to be able to shoot 45 minutes
不是摄像机换胶卷的问题
Not reload of the cameras
因为整个团队都不能再集中精神
Because it’s true this entire group can’t get on concentrate
演员就能集中那么久，所以你需要2-3分钟的休息
The actors can only concentrate for so long and you need 2-min-break, 3-min-break
正好换胶卷
during which time you reload
当你用胶片摄像机拍摄的时候
When you’re running a film camera on sight
每个人都比较严肃
everyone seems to take things a little bit more seriously
当他们听见胶卷转的时候
When they hear the film running
其实基本上听见的都是钱的声音
they hear the money running on the camera basically
每个人都全神贯注
Everybody brings an aim
我头次听说摄像机里有胶卷在转的时候
The first time I’d ever heard the word a film going through a camera
格蕾塔 葛韦格，演员
（格林伯格/亚瑟/爱情无线牵）
又兴奋又紧张
It was thrilling also make me very nervous because
因为突然间每一帧都要算钱，而我以前从未经历过
All of a sudden each take counted in a way that I never really experienced before
在你喊“开始”的瞬间感觉如何
what about that moment after you say “action”
比如对我来说，摄像机开始工作
Like for me, when that cameras rolling
我猜肯定是和钱有联系，不过
I guess maybe it’s connected to the money but...
10分钟也太有限了
the 10-minute reel is so finite
这简直就像竞技体育，你得集中再集中..
It’s almost athletic thing like focus, focus…
理查德 林克莱特，导演
（黑暗扫描仪/都市浪人/年少轻狂）
然后，“嗯这个不错”这样
Like that’s good for them
其实就是个气氛
that’s just atmosphere though
我的意思是，你要是那么想肯定感觉的到
I mean if you want that you can create that, right
丹尼 鲍尔，导演
（海滩/惊变28天/贫民窟的百万富翁）
我觉得演员的情况会不一样
I thought it could make a difference through actors
不用给一堆第二次拍摄机会
Don’t give a dozen particularly twice
我可以不断的调整到他们觉得合适
I Just infinitely give adjust whatever way they have to tell it they’ll tell it
你不会暂停也不说：“嘿，能停了么”
You didn’t ask for a break you didn’t say:”hey, can we stop”
你现在用的是数位摄像吗？--没错
You are on digital now -- yeah
我第一次经历到没有暂停的拍摄是
Though my first experience is, without which is, there is no cut
和理查德 林克莱特合作的《黑暗扫描仪》
I worked with Richard Linklater on the film called Scanner Darkly
就像--你继续吧
It just lik -- you can just go on
对，我哀求道“我们停下来吧”
Yeah, I just like “can we please stop”
停下吧~
Stop~
不，没那必要
No, we don’t have to
但是我想停下来啊！
But I want to！
罗伯特唐尼找到我说：
Robert Downey actually came up to me, and he said:
“这样工作我不行的
“I can’t work like this,
“我找不到我的拖车，我从来也没整理过自己的东西
“I never get to my trailer, I never get my shit together
“我一天站14个小时，我一直在拍啊拍啊。”
“I’m on my feet 14 hours a day, I’m shooting all the time.”
他把盛尿的石头罐子放片场了
He actually left mason jars of urine on the set
就放角落里
Just like over in the corner stuff
他会出去尿完了再放回来
just he will go off and pee in it and bring it back
拿这个跟我抗议
this is like a form of protest
以前，用赛璐珞拍片真的好兴奋啊
Previously, what’s on celluloid only really has been thrilled
那种获得赛璐珞圣杯的感觉，很神奇
to arrive a holy grail of celluloid, it’s amazing
所以我们的头几部电影是用赛璐珞拍的
so we made the first few films on celluloid
而且我做了道不错的好莱坞大餐
and I made a very big of Hollywood film
《海滩》
the beach
海滩，2000
和李奥纳多迪卡普里奥，还有很大的一个工作团队
with Leonardo Di Caprio, and a big crew
不过这一点也不适合我
and it didn’t suit me at all
感觉担子实在太重
I felt it was too much weight for me really somehow
接下来我看到了《家宴》
And so I then saw celebration
家宴，1998
不像电影，也不像眼见
wasn’t so much the film, wasn’t even a look
单纯的摄像机操作
It was the camera operating
和摄像移动
Movement of the camera
所以我找到拍摄它的人：安东尼 多德 曼妥
So I got with the guy who shot it, Anthony Dod Mantle
我觉得像是离经叛道
And I said I feel like not doing the right thing any more
“我们一起做点什么吧，用数位摄像”
“Can we do something together, Digitally”
我都不知道自己在说啥，不过觉得像个新世界
which I didn’t know what I ‘m saying by saying that It was kind like a new world anyway
接着我们就着手制作《惊变28天》
Then we came with the script 28 days later
惊变28天，2002
这是我们用消费型摄像机拍的
And we shot it on consumer cameras
但是我记得安东尼对我说过
But I remember Anthony saying to me
这个格式没问题的，不过我们这辈子也没法得奥斯卡了
It’s all vey well working in this format and he said we’ll never get an Oscar
开始的时候有个场景，斯里安墨菲要演的
There was a scene in the beginning what the character Cillian Murphy wanted it run
荒废的伦敦
A deserted London
要是用胶片，这片子怕是无法完成
We will not be able to achieve the film on film
因为我们没那么多钱去阻断交通
Because we have to stop the traffic and we did not get enough money to do it
所以我们只是短暂的挡了一会儿交通
So what we do is just hold the traffic briefly
但是因为我们是用这些摄像机拍的，能用10个一起拍
But because we run these cameras, we could use ten of them
因为太便宜了
cause it’s so cheap
而且他可以走过伦敦中心和其他区域
and he can walk through central London and areas of it
我们有10台摄像机，只要交通停止几分钟就行
We have 10 cameras of that, so you only have to stop the traffic for a few minutes
接着就有10个拍摄画面了
Then you would actually have 10 shots
这可是一大进步
That was enormous advantage
我们拿摄像机到处转
We plays cameras around
不是随机的、坏的、漫无目的的
Not coinciding not badly not loosely
我试图控制每个角度而且我知道哪些更好
I tried to control every angle and I know what few ways is best
用哪个更好
What’s gonna be used
不过之前可以任意看，来获得新的设想
But that said you can let anyone there, and have a little new guesses there
你是在拍有很小人像的广角镜头
You are in a wide shot with small figures in it
也就2-3个像素
They were just like 2-3 pixels
我是说那几乎啥也没有，就是颜色而已
I mean there’s nothing there, they were just color
颜色是比较明智的做法，要是同质拷贝到胶片上
color is wise if you put it up against exact copy of they were on film
那这张胶片会巨大无比
The film will be imagerily superior
不过你却可以偷着拍，代替性的拍，不让人知道
But you can shoot illegally, substitutedly without people knowing
你可以不照套路出牌
You could do unconventional things
这时影片的节奏
And the rhythm of film which is passed on since it began
(?)镜头的连续
(?)Cruise of lens
就都被打断了,我喜欢这种自由感
You interrupted that, I love that freedom
所以尝到甜头后，我知道这样的设计要怎么做了
And I got taste for it then, I knew which way to chalk that sequence
所以我正在做这件事，而结果也和我想要的一样
so I was gonna work on it now, that wasI want it to work
这让剪辑的工作变得特别（繁杂），因为常常有大量的材料涌入
It makes the editor’s job extraordinary cause it’s often plumbing through Masses and masses and masses material
70-80年代
In the 1970s and 80s
电气公司开始着手可以取代胶片剪辑的解决方案
electronics companies began working on solutions to replace film editing
100多年来，剪辑人员都是手动剪切粘贴胶片的
For over 100 years, editing man physically cutting and connecting pieces of film
我们以前常去剪辑室
we used to go to the editing room
他们把胶卷抽到剪切盒里
they were rolling them into the trim basket
把现在的胶片放到滚动轴上
they took the film now, and put that through the moving roll
汤姆 罗斯曼，福克斯影业首席CEO
然后像这样啪啪的把他们粘到一起
and you slap it together like this
那些戴白手套的干这个难以置信的快
you remember the white gloves and they’re incredibly fast at it
我摸到（胶片）边缘，有时候很锋利，会把手指割出血
I find a frame and Sometimes blazing and get your fingertips bloodied
这可是真的“电影上的血”啊
that’s just really the blood in the film
我是说真的血，不过现在这一切都变成神奇小按钮了
So I mean really had it and now it’s fascinating buttons
这是一张大家都熟悉的软盘...
now this is the floppy disk we all familiar…
早期的剪辑系统使用可塑磁碟
early editing systems use moldable magnetic disks
磁带机和镭射光碟
tape machines and laser disks
来存储并读取数字化的胶片
to store and read digitaled of film
这些系统大多特别贵
most of the systems are enormously very costly
费尔 曼休斯，摄影
（皇家赌场/佐罗传奇/偷天陷阱）
我想后来改变一切的第一件事应该是我知道了剪辑机器
the first thing I have read that changed everything I think it was the digital editing machine
可以花一天把胶片变成影带
which spend a daily set and converted film into tape
所以一切从这开始
so that’s started the whole thing going
我们研发了一台全数字化的图像剪辑系统
we start a picture editing system that was all digital
“editdroid”剪辑系统
我们的第一台editdroid在1980年开始工作
we had the first “editdroid” working in 1980
我们最后把它卖给了AVID
and we eventually sold the system to AVID
80年代末
by the late 1980s
AVID把数位剪辑发展成了密集型、有偿高效、全电脑控制的系统
AVID had developed digital editing into a compacted cost-effective computer-based system
我第一次看到AVID的时候
when I first saw the AVID
格雷格 伍德，剪辑
（加勒比海盗/浪人47/午夜凶铃）
我看见又小又灰暗的图像在里面
I have a dimmer image quality was block in, tiny
然后我说，这个要是在五年时间内能把图像质量提高就好了
and I said: this is gonna be really good if they give the image quality right about in 5 years time
沃特 默奇，剪辑
（现代启示录/英国病人/冷山）
为什么不试试AVID
why not try it on the AVID
我也是最早那批采用者之一
I’m also one of the earlier adopter people
我喜欢探索未知世界
I like to leap into the unknown
我记得做《英国病人》的时候
I remember on the English patient
我看着它的画面说：“天啊，我要怎么做啊”
I look at in the images and “no, how I’m gonna to be able to do this?”
德里克 安布罗西，剪辑
（致命急件）
我和老一辈的剪辑一起工作时
when I work with elder editors
他们总是提起电脑刚刚被被用到这项工作上的时候
they’ll often to talk about the time when computers were starting to come in
他们对此比较抵触，因为他们不熟悉电脑
and they were very resistant to it because they weren’t familiar with computers
他们害怕因为对电脑了解不够
they were just scared that they didn’t know enough about it
可能导致不小心按错键或是意外关机开机，然后啥都没了
if you push that button or if you accidentally turn it off wrong or turn it on wrong that everything will be gone
但你要是拿手去做这些情况不可能发生
while that could never happen if you actually physically have the film in your hand
他们觉得自己根本就没在剪辑，剪辑其实是…
they thought that was not editing, editing is…
不管胶片怎么剪辑
so when you’re editing the movie on film
都是技术而已，而艺术
that’s just technology, the art form
是操纵画面来讲故事
is the manipulation of images to tell a story
安 科兹，剪辑
（阿拉伯的劳伦斯/永不妥协/黄金罗盘）
操作起来挺难的
it was extremely difficult major that
因为我以前没用过电脑
because I haven’t used a computer
我见过老鼠（鼠标）到处跑，不过可不是在剪辑室
I’ve seen a mouse somewhere across the floor but not in the editing room
不过我学了，还用了很长一段时间
but I learnt and I keep the machine quite a bit
不过不用电脑我也无所谓，我也喜欢这样
but once I don’t doing on it that’s ok and I like it
剪辑处没有胶片
there’s no film in the editing bay
一切都
it’s all…
克里斯 莱本森
（爱丽丝梦游仙境/世界末日/壮志凌云）
一切都好安静
it’s quite
我听不见以前常听见的“rururu”的声音
I don’t hear I used to hear the “rururu…”
就是工作台上的卷轴发出的
the reel on the benches
一直都是非常吵杂的工作环境
it was very noisy kind of buzzing atmosphere
不过现在特别安静，好像所有的声音都能像蜡烛一样被烧掉
and now it’s very quite, almost like that you can burn any sound like candles
数位技术把事情变得高效
digital bring you the speed and almost
不过同时也在挑战你：“我能想那么快吗？”
challenge you the sense of “can I think that fast”
“我有时间喘气吗”
“do I need time to breathe?”
有时年轻的剪辑总是充满兴趣，还做着非常有趣的工作
sometime are young editors are over-interesting and doing extremely interesting work
但他们不总是有时间安静坐下来并思考自己到底在做什么
but they don’t always have the time to sit back and think about what they are doing
不过我想他们要是用胶片来工作
and I think if they work on film
就必须要训练他们的思想来实现这点
they probably have to train their mind to do that
真的是另一种思考方式
so it’s a different way of thinking, really
胶片用条条框框折磨你
film torture you with discipline
持摄影机的人，1929
用电脑的话就没那么痛苦了
that it’s gone a little bit from the computer
因为一旦你动了剪子
because you once put the scissors in
就得拿胶布再粘起来
you’ve been got to join it back with sticky tape
再连到机器上
and bond it through the machine
这个过程你是关键
you’re much more decisive about that
剪辑过程变更好了吗？
has editing got any better?
就因为选择变多了？我觉得不一定
because it’s infinite the choice? I’m not so sure
洛伦佐 狄波纳文图拉，制片
（变形金刚/特工绍特/窗台上的男人）
不过有件事情比较肯定，现在的很多电影更烂了
but I’m pretty sure that a lot of movies are getting worse
因为你将它推向死亡
because you manipulate it to death
我们会失去很多东西
we may lost something
《阿拉伯的劳伦斯》中，当他划亮火柴
the cutting that Lawrence of Arabia when he blows the match up
看得出来您有着有趣的幽默感
this is recognized that you have a funny sense of fun
这只是写在剧本里
that was the solving script
不过要是有我们今天的数字技术
and if you’ve been on digital as we have on that today
看准就行了
you just have to see it
不过那时候，电影都是一段一段粘起来的
in those days, the film were bonded together like that
就靠剪辑
just with the direct cut
所以当我们看到这个，我们都惊呼不可思议
so when we saw it, we got “wow, that’s fantastic”
想想吧，当时那种感情
just work it, just imagine it, when you feel that feeling
作为影像和声音的承载体，数位拥有不可思议的可塑性
digital is unbelievably malleable plastic of imatery and sound
这很有吸引力，因为我们要的就是可塑性
and that’s seductive, because that’s all we do
我们是图像和声音的雕塑者
we are sculptors of images and sound
不是说胶片就做不了
it’s not that you can’t do it in film
就是操作麻烦，而且想做好很难
it’s just harder to do that and make it look good
在数字技术不断发展的同时
as digital technology continued to grow
计算机生成图像，及通常说的CGI
computer generated images or CGI
越来越多的出现在电影中
were appearing more and more in movies
大都会，1927
视觉特效，或VFX
visul FX or VFX (Visual Special Effects)
自电影成长初期起就成为了电影制作的一部分
have been part of film making since the earliest years
35:11
伊阿宋与金羊毛，1963
摄像技巧，灯光技术，精细模型和实验室操作
camera tricks, lighting techniques, elaborate models and lab processes
第三类接触，1977
都被用作改变真实并提高电影体验
have all been used to alter realty and enhance the movie going experience
夺宝奇兵：法柜奇兵，1981
星际迷航2，1982
好多电影都不是想拍就拍的
on many films that the number is unpredicted you can’t go out and shoot
所以那些你想要的画面就只能想办法制作
so the images you need to see you need to be manufactory in somewhere
约翰 科诺，工业光魔视觉特效总监
（阿凡达/加勒比海盗/星球大战1-3）
帝国反击战，1980
作为视觉特效总监你得明白
things of visual FX supervisor called on you to understand
蒂姆 韦伯，FrameStone 视觉特效总监
（阿凡达/黑暗骑士/人类之子）
你得了解到这个世界的时时刻刻方方面面
a huge variety of different aspect of the world around us at any one time
你还得明白光反射不同表面的物理知识
you also understand the physics of the way that light reacts of different surfaces
独立日，1996
你得明白动画绘制，人怎么动，其他的东西怎么做
you got to understand animation, you got understand the way people move creatures move
你得同时成为艺术家和技师
you have to be an artist and a technician at the same time
这是个奇妙的组合
that’s an interesting combination
丹尼斯 莫伦，工业光魔视觉特效总监
（星球大战/E.T./侏罗纪公园）
最初的视觉特效师和头一百年特效师干的没什么两样
originally visual FX was done was the first hundred years of the FX was done
用模型和胶片摄影，能做的实际很有限
they were done with models and with film cameras and they are very limit what you can do
我们花费了很多时间、经历和人们的努力来做《星球大战》
but a lot of time and energy and people worked a lot to being able to make star wars film
22年前我入行的时候
when I first doing this about 22 years ago
我学习的环境是真实的，有个舞台
the environment I learned it was a physical one, it was a stage
亚当 瓦尔德斯，MPC视觉特效总监
（指环王/纳尼亚传奇/星河战队）
微缩模型、灯光和其他的一些东西都在那
miniatures, camera lights and everything in it
做真实模型有个好处
the great thing about making real stuff is
你要用上全部感情和身体感知
you got to use all of your senses and your physical perceptions and
接着3个人和其他挑剔的模型师站过去
stand there are 3 different people and critical modelers
讨论着某件东西在真实光源中是有多酷，那感觉真满足
talks about how cool something looks like in real lighting is pretty satisfying
拍出来的东西送去用光学印片机
and all those photography was on the optical printer in the end
就是一部大机器，把多层胶片压在一起
that’s a large device that actually compress layers of film together
然后用这些组合胶片曝光
and creates new exposures of the film so you can combine it the layers
这样组合出来的图像就是电影的最终效果
with images into the final one that you’ve seen in the movie
视觉特效部，就是实打实的把胶片一张又一张再一张的叠起来
the visual FX department was literately sandwiching one piece of film next to another piece of film next to another piece of film
乔纳森 福克纳，FrameStone视觉特效总监
（阿凡达/大侦探福尔摩斯/V字仇杀队）
而这个过程可能引入巨大的人为破坏
and that really introduces huge mantle depredation
1978年，我们刚刚完成了《星球大战》
in 1978, we had just finished star wars
那时候我们没找到更好的数字方法，所以制作还是比较艰苦的
we don’t find digital sharps in there which were very very cruel
比如那个场景的数学图像和其他的一些东西
the diagram with that part kind of thing
不过我知道有些人正在用数位技术做电影
but I knew a lot of guys, they were working with the digital film
所以我成立了一个电脑部门
so I start a computer division
我们在那给工业光魔创立了皮克斯
we developed the pixar computer for ILM
我现在就在我们工业光魔3个电脑室之一
I’m right now with one of our three computer rooms we have here in ILM
我们在这有
and what we have here are
时时刻刻都在运行的千千万万的电脑程序
thousand and millions of cycles of computer power going by every single second
我有点强迫他们尽可能取工业光魔的资源
so I kind push the staff use as much as they could in ILM
在视觉组能够提供的情况下
with this graphics crew that we have
星际迷航2， 1982
令人兴奋的是
the exciting about it was
（数字制作）没那么多规矩
they didn’t feel like with a lot of rules
一点也不像“狂野西部”
they really don’t seems like kind of wild west
扫描胶片到电脑上并在那做修改成为可能
it starts to become possible to scanning film and bringing the film into the computer and make changes to that
数字化胶片的好处太多了
massive advantage to digitizing your film
可以不必造成任何破坏
with that you couldn’t get any depredation
一旦数字化，就是一堆0和1
once it’s digital there is 1s and 0s
这些0和1在整个过程中都不会改变
they just stay 1s and 0s all the way down the pipe
数字技术对特效来说变得非常重要
(?)digital became important for a FX point of view
特效斗兽场中的第一条通途
the first path through the system was in the FX arena
利用数字技术来让幻想成真
it was using digital technology to realize visions
要是能把胶片转换成数字
if you can take piece of film you can turn it into numbers
你能够操纵这些数字再变回影片
you can manipulate those numbers through back to the film
不过却没有任何限制
but there’s no limit to what you could do
整个世界的大门由此打开
the entire world is wide open
我们所制作的第一个完全数字化的画面
the first real image that we did that was completely digital
是在《少年福尔摩斯》中
was in young Sherlock Holmes
少年福尔摩斯，1985
我们有个彩色玻璃做的角色
we have a character made of stained glass
那个玻璃看起来像真的
the glass actually looks real
不像画出来的
not like a graphic in that sort
花了6个月和7场拍摄，很复杂
and it took 6 months and 7 shots which was pretty complicated
不过最后效果出来的时候很不错
but it’s amazing we got it done at that time
詹姆斯 卡梅伦，导演/制片
（阿凡达/泰坦尼克号/终结者）
乔治总是在数字技术上更进一步
George was always progressive about digital
而且技术平台的交互性让人觉得很舒服，很早以前就是如此
(?)and something about the fetch communer you just got comfortable with it really early on
深渊，1989
终结者2，1991
侏罗纪公园，1993
小猪宝贝，1995
我现在要当一只羊
I was just trying to be a sheep now
哼，狼已经来了
huh, that wolf’s in the world already
第五元素，1997
星河战队，1997
那时我们还是用胶片摄像机
now we are still shooting on film
还不能直接使用数字拍摄
we ain’t able to shoot on digital cameras yet
泰坦尼克号，1997
不过所有的后期制作已经提前数字化了
but all of the post processes is start in front of line
你怎么进到电脑里的
how did you going into the computer?
我拿出手来让他们照张相
I would have my hand and then they would take a picture of it
黑客帝国，1999
然后会有台电脑
and then there was a computer
把所有都处理成银一样，那就是我的手
it would do the animation of all look silver and silver hand
然后他们就把这个放到大屏幕上给你看
and they will show you on the movie screen
我们在《黑客帝国三部曲》的经验是
our experience on the trilogy
拉娜/安迪 沃卓斯基，导演/制片
（黑客帝国三部曲/极速赛车手/云图）
当你意识到这点其实很有趣
what was really interesting with that you realize
你其实是在碰运气
you are really creating these images in toss
你拍不到这些而只能在电脑上做
you couldn’t shoot the image you made the image in the computer
90年代中后期
middle to late 90s
(?)您是如何开始进行视觉特效的？
I guess its standard death… visual FX… where do you get in
我们在工业光魔有个做特效的项目
we have program in ILM doing our FX
我们要把胶片转换为数字才能完成
we have convert from film to digital in order to do it
这得花一大笔钱，现在我们已经不用再进行这样的转换了
it’s a huge amount of money just now we don’t have to convert any more
胶片很难处理
film is cumbersome
我想省钱省时间，我要解决这个问题
so I just want to take my money and my time, I’m gonna fix it
我们去索尼公司和他们说
when we went to SONY, and we said:
我们帮你造个数位摄像机吧
we would like to help you work with you to build a digital camera
他（卢卡斯）决定星战（前传）第二部要用数位技术拍
he was on the determine that star wars episode 2 can kind be shot digitally
这就意味所有的工作都要为
that means get all that work out, get pipeline figured out for doing
数位拍摄电影准备好
our production at digital cameras
早期数位摄像的问题之一是
one of the problems with early digital capture
图像的分辨率
was resolution
分辨率是由很多因素决定的
resolution is depended on many factors
不过最基本的因素是
but in the most basic terms
摄像机所能记录的像素数
it is the number of pixels that the camera can record
像素数越多，分辨率越高
the more pixels you had, the higher the resolution
图像所具有的细节也更多
and more detail a image would have
一部标准标清摄像机
a typical standard definition of resolution of SD camera
通常具有720 × 480的分辨率
usually have a resolution of about 720 × 480 pixels
转折发生在2000年
really, the turn-in point was in the year 2000
我们推出了F900，第一部高清摄像机
we came out with F900 camera which was the first high definition camera
在那之前，所有的数位拍摄看起来都像录像
before that, whatever you look was really look like video
高清摄像机可以达到1920分辨率，也就是2K以下
high definition cameras record resolution about 1920 pixels across, just under 2K
克隆人进攻，2002
2002年
in 2002
我们完成了《克隆人的进攻》
we did the attack of the clones
这是第一部高清摄像的电影
it was the first major feature that was shot high definition
乔治在《星球大战》中
what George did in star wars movie
实验性的使用了高清摄像机
was take experimental HD camera
其画面质量已达到胶片水平
and ply it to feature film parallel
卢卡斯影业，旧金山，加利福尼亚
这在当时是不可想象的
that was unthinkable at that time
不仅仅是对电影协会
it meant that it was around the entire film community
更是对胶片电影本身
but more deeply mean it was around film itself
那时的好莱坞人们经历了严重两极分化的时期
it became a really really polarizing time for a lot people in Hollywood
有好多大会都说我是个骗子
we got a lot bit big meetings saying I was doubling carneys
说我会摧毁电影工业和好多人的工作
I was going to destroy our industry, I was going to destroy our jobs
在影院里他们说：“他嘴上说《克隆人的进攻》是数字拍的，其实不是，
in theater that he said he shot the attack of the clones digitally, but he didn’t
“我们听说他其实还是用胶片拍的，
we have the words that he actually used film cameras
“他没用数位拍摄，他欺骗了所有人。”
he’s not shooting digital, he’s lying to everybody
在1920分辨率下，我觉得画质真的令人震惊
with 1900, I thought the images out there is truly appalling
就是影院品质
I think that was a cinematic camera at all
早些年，我不觉得数位摄像（和胶片）一样
in early years, I didn’t feel digital capture or digital production was the same
他们总说：看，能看出差别吗？
they would always say: see, if you can tell the difference?
然后我说能
and I could tell the difference
我们的F900并非为拍摄电影而设计
our first F900 wasn’t designed like a film camera
不过乔治卢卡斯用它拍了《星战前传》后
of course George Lucas had it shoot star wars
就再也不打算用胶片拍电影了
like he wouldn’t shoot another film on film again
这在好莱坞也获得了很多支持
and that created quite enough pro in Hollywood
数字技术和数字摄像机
digital technology and digital cameras
看起来像是一种对
looked like a threat to people’s existence in
人们思考和工作方式的威胁
way of thinking and way of working
电影制作是艺术
film making is an art
对于传统的电影制作者来说
to the traditional film maker it looks like
我们像是在糟蹋艺术
we were messing around with art
他们说你为什么不思进取
and they said why you went backwards, you know what
不过也有很多人说这是有必要的，是前进的必要环节
but it’s a lot said about the necessity, a link back be able to spring forward
天行者牧场，加利福尼亚
10年前乔治卢卡斯把大家聚在一起
George Lucas putting up together everybody 10 years ago
在旧金山的天行者牧场开了个会
what a conference he gave the ranch up in San Francisco
澄清了一个事实
and went object of our roles about the idea that
数字技术是不是会把电影摄制终结
digital will put an end to the old cinematography
他说这就是另一个工具而已
he point out that it’s just another tool
而且这一点不错
and that’s true
当人们看到了乔治卢卡斯的测试
when people saw George Lucas’s test
他们说，这可行不通
they said: that’s not gonna work
不过也有人想，我大概会在10年内接受它
it was the same sort of close mind that we’re gonna work 10 years to adopt that
我得等等，有人上我就上，我上了大家就都上了
I was gonna wait a little, if someone followed I will be one, I will one and that will be entire
我知道是时候了，总是这样的
I know the time is it, it always does
《墨西哥往事》片场，2003，设备：SONY F900
我知道这是某件大事的开端
I can tell this is gonna be the beginning of something big
而我想成为这件事的一部分
and I want to be there for that
但是画面很烂啊
but the image sucked
画面没那么差，就是不如胶片拍的好
the image wasn’t bad, but the image wasn’t as good as film
不过却可以让我做一些从没法完成的事
but it allowed me to do something you cannot ever done
罪恶之城，2005
我想到了《罪恶之城》那本书，我知道该怎么做了
I picked it in my sin city book, and I know how to do it now
我应该用数字拍摄
I got shoot this digital
可以就像漫画书里表现的那样
I can make it looks just like the book
夜晚如地狱般炎热
the night is hot as hell
楼上有一位女神
upstairs there is a goddess
她说她要我
she’s telling me she wants me
如果不是数字摄像，《罪恶之城》不会存在
sin city will not exist if I didn’t choose digital film
我甚至根本想不到去拍
I wouldn’t even thought to do it
他们想要一些事情推动艺术形式的发展
they wish to do thing that push the art form
技术推动艺术，而艺术也推动技术发展
technology push the art and art push technology
《罪恶之城》的出现石破天惊
sin city came out hit people like break eggs
他们不知道他们看的是什么
they have no idea what they are looking at
他们想要在表面下的有些东西消失
something hiding from it under rock and hopes it goes away
你完成了一些人么认为不可能的事情
you end it up doing something that people didn’t realize was possible
效果如此惊人，你知道一切皆有可能
it’s so amazed that which it had that knowing anything is possible
这个系统有着你从没感受过的颜色广度
the system got better for color and you didn’t working of that color space
电影经过了拍摄、剪辑和视觉特效合成后
after the movie is shot, edited and VFX being added
色彩配光师会在实验室里继续调整电影的画面
the colorist or color timers in the lab make adjustment to the look of the movie
在传统化学摄像法中
in the traditional photo chemical method
底片要经过显影和印片
the negative is developed in print is made
在黑白电影时代的配光
timing goes back to the days when there’s only black and white
唐 希亚那，特艺彩色配光师
这些画面展示了旧时实验室的暗房操作
these scenes showed the dark room operations of the laboratory in the old days
主要就是自己看底片
I had my job it’s looked at the negative and the side how long
以及要在显影床里泡多长时间
it would have to stay in the beds
第一次如果不行…
if the first wasn’t right…
那就继续泡
dunk, dunk again
所以这就是配光跟时间的关系
so, it was time related
随着彩色胶片的发明
with the advent of color film
绿野仙踪，1939
配光师的工作也变成更具创造性的过程
the timers became more involved into creative process
实验室里，色彩配光师、摄影指导和导演决定
at the lab, the color timer, DP, and director determine the look
最后的印片样式，以在影院上映
for the final prints there will be seen by the public in the theaters
化学摄像中唯一能做的调整是
the only adjustment that can make photo chemically
红绿蓝三原色及亮度的整合
are color bands between red, green, blue and brightness
我们的工作就是达成导演和摄影想要的结果
our job basically is to achieve the vision of the director and the DP
泰瑞 海格，特艺彩色配光师
并在胶片上实现
and make it happen on a piece of film
我会和导演和摄影坐在一起
like I was sitting with the director and the DP
他们会说这有点太红或太模糊或太蓝了
and they’ll say that is a little bit too red, too smear, too blue
然后我们就在头脑中调整
and we will manipulated in our minds as how much to
怎么改变或做不同的对比度平衡
change it or to make different cuts balance with each othe
胶片时代的配光
when the time was on the film
基本上靠脑袋想然后用嘴说
they got to do it pretty much from the head by the tuition
是么
yeah
这很难的，非常难
it was hard, very hard
安德烈 巴克维亚，摄影
（非法入侵/生死时速/魔鬼代言人）
所以为了做到要付出很多劳动和艺术心血
so in order to do this there were a lot of art and labor involved in it
为了达到最后的效果，这些人很努力
these people really work hard to that, achieve that
配光是个很令人沮丧的过程
I still found it very very frustrating that timing process
在片子播放的时候在不停的说，还要跟上剪辑的速度
you kind of talking over the thing while it’s running and trying to keep up with the cuts
史蒂文 索德伯格，导演/摄影
（11罗汉/切格瓦拉/传染病）
然后还有些专业词汇
and saying that I don’t know it’s a little science to me
他们就不停地把脚注写下来
something in the guys they are trying to write it down, write the footage down
这个过程一直就是这样，感觉很疯狂
as it goes on you can’t stop and that seems crazy
数字色彩校正工具首先被使用到短片中
digital color correction tools were first to use for shorter pieces
例如广告和音乐录像
such as commercials and music videos
在音乐录像中配光
basting time in music videos
史蒂凡 索纳菲德，DI配光师
（借刀杀人/斯巴达300勇士/爱丽丝漫游仙境）
我们完成了最疯狂的和最具突破性的视觉体验
and we came up some of the craziest and ground breaking visual images
而来到这样的一个房间
and it was just amazing ability to come to a room like this
制作人么从没见过的画面，本来就很神奇
and manipulate something to create images that people never seen before
数字色彩校正开始取代传统的化学摄像色彩配光
digital color correction began replacing traditional photo chemical methods of color timing
吉尔 博格丹诺维茨，DI配光师
（胡佛/老爷车/灵魂歌王）
我的工作就是保证制作人能够达到他们想要的效果
my job is to be able to make sure the creatives get everything what they want
保证摄影得到他要的对比度
make sure the photographer gets the pilot of contrast that he wants
保证导演想要的电影色调
and the director gets the feelings he wants around movie
保证我们能看到演员的眼睛
make sure that we can see all actors eyes
饱含他想要的感情
and see all the emotion that he wants to see
现在我来建立一个我们说的能量窗
I can now start building what we call power window
在这我可以做任何我想要的改动
in a power window I can change any kind of view I want
比如左边的这些树
I just want these trees over on the left
我可以改变它们的颜色
I can take the color that I want on those trees
我能把它隔离出来
and I can isolate it
接着就可以变成任何颜色了
now I can change those trees in any color I want
导演和摄影会来和我们一起几周
the cinematographer and the director coming and we spend a couple of weeks
蒂姆 斯蒂潘，DI配光师
（黑天鹅/摔跤王/切格瓦拉）
把电影调整到更好看
grading the film and give it that look make it look beautiful
到他们想要的程度
however they want to look
只要合理我都能做到，这种感觉很棒
I had a great feeling that I can do just about anything you asked me to do it in reason
是谁发明了这个系统呢
who invented this process
你知道曾经用在音乐录像上的技术吧
the same technology people used for music videos
把画面变得很酷
create how cool it looks
而现在的技术是过去的10年间发展起来的
and basically what happened was over last 10 years
只是更加进化并自由了
it just evolved and it becomes a lot more free mind
逃狱三王，2000
这是第一部从头到尾
Over there were art that it was really the first movie
使用特效配光的电影
where at basically that every single frame was the visual fact
为了达到效果用数字技术配光
So its all color times digitally for the look
所以这是第一部DI
So it’s a first DI. It’s just kind of…
罗杰迪金斯（《逃狱三王》摄影）在这说：
Roger Deakins sit in the room and saying
我不能用化学摄像法
I can’t get what I want in photo chemical
因为每次我想要给配光成美丽的金色蓝天就全没了
Because every time I color time this nice golden color I lose my blue sky
我该怎么办啊
what am I gonna do
有点太黄了是不是
it’s a little bit yellow isn’t it
应该更棕一点
should be sort of more brown
所以我跟他说
So he came in to testing actually I sat with him and showed him
我们能做，我们能做到画面中的每个细节
Ok we can key it, what we do is we can basically affect everything in the image
不过蓝天是不行了，因为这会毁掉其他的东西
except for the blue in the sky also they will ruin overalls
所以蓝色就不能用了
so the blue’s in wardrobe
不过其他的，像这些绿树如果不是你要的颜色
but everything else like the green trees that are not in pilot that you want
我们可以把它调成棕黄色
we can exaggerate them in brown gold
所以这部电影的画面很成功
so out of the successive look for the movie
接着其他的人也跟进
and other people catching on and say
“哇，我也可以试试那个”
woo, I can use that in
接着（DI）就变得流行起来
it just became more and more popular
化学摄像配光法真的很令人沮丧
timing is a very frustrating process on photo chemical
很残酷而且也基本上干不了什么
it’s very cruelled, hardly to do anything
不过DI就不一样了
that’s a whole thing about DI
我可以圈出一个小东西，可以让一张脸更红
while I can go in to circle a little thing and make a face a little bit redder
还可以隔离背景，简直是天堂啊
and bring out the background I was just in heaven
太不可思议了，我可以做任何事来完成一部电影
it’s amazing I can do anything to success movie
现在回想比较有趣的是
what I find interesting now looking back
从我最初成为摄影师的时候开始
to the beginning of experimentation of as a cinematographer like myself
暖暖内含光，2004
从电影诞生到数码世界
Going from a film original and the digital world
我们一直在寻找能够控制画面并更具操控力的方法
Seeking more control of the image and being able to manipulate the image more
不过现在却是我们失去了更多控制
And now we actually have lost control
我们放弃了底片，也放弃了成品
Because we then give away our negative, give away our product
能拿到的人都可以对其进行操作
Anybody can take it after that and can manipulate it
这是最后成品很重要的一个方面
(?)this cording is really an important aspect of the final product
我是把电影做成更好的样子
I’m the one that pushing these buttons to make your film look a certain way
虽然我要接受指示
Yes I’m getting the direction but
不过这需要很多自己的东西来承担这个责任
it’s a lot of my own confidence to crane that certain amount
把它带领到一个正确的方向
And push that into a certain direction
所以我基本上是真正接触它的人
So I’m kind of like the last person who really gets the touch of it
摄影和配光师之间开始变得对抗
It started to become very adversarial between cinematographer and colorist
因为他们都想“他不是决定电影画面的人，我才是”
because they were like “he shouldn’t be determining how the film looks like, I do that”
不过过程之美就在于这是个团队啊
the beauty of this process is it’s a team
这有可能把DP的权利削弱
it could take the power away from the DP but I think it’s
不过我认为作为摄影的工作就是尽量让拍出来的东西好看
your job as a cinematographer to try your best to see it through the eye
他们会尽量控制DI
They will do everything to make sure they president the DI
来实现他们所想的画面
And that will supervise that the dare vision they intend was executed
迈克尔 包豪斯，摄影
（纽约黑帮/好家伙/无间道风云）
在《纽约黑帮》里，他们要我做DI
In gangs of New York  they offer me to do a DI
纽约黑帮，2002
因为每件事都已经准备好了
But because everything was built for us
我们从大屏幕上看见的就是我们想要的
what we had on screen was exactly what we wanted
并不需要DI去改变什么
It didn’t have to have a DI to change everything
我通常都是通过摄像机
but I’m trying always to do it in camera
用光，滤镜和镜头来调整图像
and with lighting and with filters and lenses
而不是拍完了用DI
But not later in the DI
不过如果你有个特别的故事
OK, if you have a special story
需要你改变现实
when you need to change the reality
那DI就的确是个好东西
Then the DI is something wonderful
因为你可以在画面上实现你想做的一切
because you can do whatever you want in the image
这很不错
which can be great, which can be wonderful
一旦电影数字化的拷贝完成了
Once we get done digitally clap cracking your movie
我们会做一份全新的底片去印片
We make a brand new negative and then make a print of that negative
然后我们会对比数字和印片
then we look at the print versus the data in the side by side fashion
把印片和数字匹配
And we dealt in the print to match the data
处理成需要的样子
To make the print exact the way it should
你对制作母片的工作有什么感觉
How do you feel about you do all these work to have a pristine
有些印片很完美，有些就（不那么好）
and you got to have some prints perfect, and some prints…
完成之后你能放得下么
Will you let it go once you created it?
说实话去电影院的时候
honestly the truth of the fact is that when you go to a theater
你看到了几周心血的最终版
You watch that prints used to spend weeks of labor on
其实每家影院都不一样
Every theater looks different
放映机的光照强度不一样
They have the lumination on their projector in different level
还有其他的许多原因
or other so many variables
我们真正担心的改变画面的东西实际上是放映机
The real alter alternatively from the picture we used to worry about is projections
声音可大可小
Sounds could be loud and low
演员的头可能看见也可能看不见
You can see the head of the actor or not
因为放出框了，他们（放映员）挺忙的
Cause they can frame you out, cause they’re busy
总有事情要做
They got things to do
可能一卷胶片发蓝，另一卷发黄
film come up one reel be blue and another reel be brown
都是因为放映机
because use the projector like
我们曾经还挺享受这个，因为是电影的一部分嘛
we got to enjoy that because that’s the part of film
我看到印片总是失望
it’s always a huge disappointment for me to see a film print
因为真是太让人郁闷了
because it’s depressing
一点也不清晰，没个分明的断点
it’s not sharp, it does not have any snap
摇摇晃晃，脏兮兮，相当可恨
it’s shaking, it’s dirty, I hate it
我把它放大巨大的显示屏上
I put it in the tremendous monitor effort
乔司 维克诺，摄影
（潜艇风暴/全面回忆/星河战队）
就是为了我所想的影响成真
To make my images the way I have them in mind
我为此制作它们，在摄像机上完成它们
And I create them; I have them on the finish product in the camera
不过看看后来呢
But what happens afterwards
影院里电影的质量真是不堪目睹
The quality of film is terrible at theater
每个好莱坞人都说：
And anybody in Hollywood they say:
“天啊，在摄像机上看着可不是这样啊”
“Oh, it’s not that of camera, no”
所以他们从来不去电影院，看看真正的影院放映是个什么样子
so they never go to a theater to see it in the real theater
《泰坦尼克号》播放的次数太多了，我们的印片实际已经散架了
Titanic plays so long in theaters we actually had our prints fell apart
早些时候从放映机里掉出来摔碎了
They’d early just dropped out the projectors and in pieces
所以我们绞尽脑汁去获得更好的放映质量
So we were struggling of trying to get qualities in the theaters
事实是，如果使用数码放映
And out of that came the fact that if it was digital
那效果就很棒了，没有划痕，也不会被撕裂
You have a brilliant thing, you wouldn’t have to scratch it, you wouldn’t have to tear it
…这部电影已经席卷了…
…the movie has been overwhelming…
1999年，我们实现了数字放映《幽灵的威胁》
In 1999, we were able to project phantom menace digitally
2家在纽约，2家在洛杉矶
We have 2 theaters in New York, 2 theaters in LA
那是主流好莱坞电影第一次用数字放映
And that was the first time that major Hollywood movie projected digitally
那时候全国也就40家（数字放映影院）
There were up to 40 there in this country
99年的时候
Just for in 99
2002年，有150家多点
By 2002, there were still over 150
不过已经落后了
The post flow was already there
全都数字化了
it is all digital
所以电影工业的其它也会跟进
And the rest of the industry was going there
声音已经数字化了，剪辑方式也是
Sound was already got there, Editorial was got there
摄像机拖后腿了
The camera is lagging behind
借刀杀人，2004
新的公司开始发展高清摄像机
New companies began to develop high definition cameras
其它的好莱坞电影也开始跟随卢卡斯脚步
And the other Hollywood films followed Lucas’s lead
迈克尔曼的《借刀杀人》使用了汤姆森蝰蛇
Michael Mann’s  Collateral used the Thomson viper
这是一架在黑暗环境中优于胶片摄影机的高清摄像机
a HD camera that outperform film in shooting darker enviroments
设备：汤姆森蝰蛇，2004
迈克尔想要在夜里也能看见
Micheal wants to see into the night
迪奥 毕博，摄影
（借刀杀人/绿灯侠/芝加哥）
对于数位摄像机来说这是大显身手的时间
and that point is really best time for digital cameras
把（摄像）边界推向数字摄像机所擅长的方面
twit up and pushed the boundry on what digital was capable of
《借刀杀人》有意思在哪
Collateral is interesting that
它看起来完全是我们所见的那种
it was suppose to look exactly the way it looks
室外的纽约在晚上不是黑的
The New York outside at night you don’t see black
你可以看见整个城市有
You see all around the city of
绿色，大红，紫色的光和天空的雾霭
Green, magenta, purple lights and haze in the sky
你可以看见所有这些疯狂的颜色
you just see all these crazy colors
能够捕获这样的影像，只能用数位摄像机
the only way that capture them at that time was digitally
现在都在说晚上照相的事
you got a lot of this on night talking on photography going now
不过就是用了不同感光度的CCD
this just using the different sensitivities of your CCD chips
晚上能够捕捉更多的紫外线
it seizes a little more UV spectrum
所以就鼓励电影人去拍不同的夜景
so you got film makers try to use that to give a different ascetic to night time lighting
不过对我来说这些还是和录像差不多
(?)but to me it’s still of all we’re telling the flame of video
蝰蛇摄像机的出现告诉我
the viper was the first camera that really told me that
数码时代强劲崛起
the digital age was right jetting up in a tensity
数位摄像机竞争将随即而至
I can see the foot race and the cameras coming
2005年，潘那维申，胶片摄像机制造的先驱
In 2005, Panavision, an established force in the film camera business
进行了对单传感器摄像机的一系列动作
Made a serial push into digital with large sensor of single chip camera
我们开始将这视作一种真正的影片格式
We started looking at this as real format
鲍勃 哈维，潘纳维申全球市场部高级副总裁
我们觉得最好是我们来设计一台
And we decided the best thing we can do is design
我叫它“能用影带的胶片摄像机”
What I used to call it a film camera that takes tape
然后我们开始着手于“创世”
And that’s when we started drawing up the genesis
设备：潘纳维申 创世，2005
“创世”具有全幅45mm芯片
“Genesis” is a full frame, 45mm chip
这可以使影像获得和胶片相似的景深
that allows depth of field very similar to film
而且可以使用我们的45mm镜头
And we can use all our 45mm lenses
总共有上千种
Which total for thousands, literally
我们和索尼合作
And we went to the work partner up to SONY on it
他们负责设计电器元件
they design the electronics and we put it together
接着第一台被用于电影正片制作的
and we introduced the first full frame digital camera
全幅摄像机就诞生了
For making feature films
“创世”的画质超级高，因为潘那维申制造嘛
The “genesis” was high to hell because it’s from Panavision
还有潘那维申专用特级系统
And it was so designing A system for Panavision
最好的是还能使用潘那维申的镜头
The good about it was it took Panavision lenses
具有全幅传感器
It was with a 35mm sensor
而“蝰蛇”的只是2/3寸传感器
While the viper used 2/3’’ sensor
超人归来，2006
人们想获得和35mm胶片一样的感受
people wanted the same feel same look they got from 35mm
“创世”能够做到
which caught what you got with “genesis”
而且画面超好
And it gave pretty good images
这是我们为电影制作精心设计的
We were very careful to design it for film crews
要是说对比以前有什么变化
So the transition, if there’s going to be one
那就是制作电影更加简便
Would be easy for the people making movies
迪恩塞姆勒因为《与狼共舞》获得了学院奖
Dean Semler who was academic award cinematographer, financer of dance with wolves
他在墨西哥拍摄《启示录》的时候
Shot  apocalypto down in Mexico
《启示录》片场，2006
那的温度有100（华氏），湿度200
where the tempreture was 100 degrees and humility was 200
而且基本没变化（不停工）
And never had a second of down time
他感觉这就和摄像机一样
He felt it was like a film camera
35磅重
It’s 35 ponds
他妈的破机器有这么大
Fucking cameras this big
在顶上还有一个像胶卷盒的东西
And on the top of it, it looks like film magazine
录像机和机身连在一起
The recorder attached to it
和胶卷盒一样
The same way the mag will attach at the top on the back
我想看看刚拍了什么
I want to see what we just got shot
能回放吗
does it a playback off that?
不能，就和底片一样
no, you never touch that like original negative
我就直说了
so if you see I get straight
你和索尼在摄像机研发上花了几百万
you got to spend how many millions developing camera with SONY
然后你告诉我不能回看
and I can’t play the HD back to look at it
因为这是底片吗？
because that’s the negative?
迈阿密风云，2006，数字拍摄
在06/07年的时候
where we were in those 06, 07
我们已经有了不错的色度和分辨率
we had the color space and the revolution
不过动态范围还不行
but we didn’t have the dynamic range
*动态范围：亮度反差的范围*
所以取景的时候一定要小心
so we had to be careful on the sight
动态范围是硬伤
dynamic range is veto
对我来说动态范围比什么都总要
dynamic range is more important than anything to me
这也拖慢了我换数位摄像的进程
so that really me slow down to shoot digitally
看看动态范围的事吧
if you have thought of the range
要是黑与白本来的感觉是这样
if the dark and bright is felt like this
潜艇风暴，1981，胶片拍摄
要使用数位拍摄
as shoot in digital
就没有这么宽的范围了
you don’t have this wide range
填不满光亮和黑暗之间的空间
which fill the heights between the blacks and the lights
所以亮些的没有了
so whatever up here is cut off
暗些的也没有了
and whatever down there is also cut off
沃利 菲斯特，摄影
（黑暗骑士/盗梦空间/记忆碎片）
我就是不知道它怎么能能让我达到想要的效果
I just don’t feel how it is allowed to enable me to do what I want to do
数字拍摄
你不能指望5档过度曝光还能看到什么
you can’t overexpose by 5 stops and still have something in the image
你也不能指望4档曝光不足还能看到些什么
you can’t underexpose it by 4 stops and still have traces in the image
我觉得只能是一片空白
I think you’ll find plain in those areas
在2005年，吉姆詹那德，价值数十亿的太阳镜和运动服饰公司
in 2005, Jim Jannard, the founder and owner of the multi billion-dollar
Oakley的创始人和拥有者
sunglass and sports apparel company, Oakley
开始制作一架面向影院市场的数位摄像机
set out to create a new cinematic affordable digital camera
吉姆 詹那德，RED数位电影创始人
数字对胶片不够尊重
digital wasn’t paying enough respect to film
也不如胶片好
it wasn’t as good as film
对我来说一切皆可更好
and to me everything in the world can and will be made better
就看何时何人了
the only question is when and by whom
取代胶片的运动开始了
there was a technological movements towards the eventual replacement of film
泰德 施洛维茨，RED数位电影
当时的现象就是，主流厂商
what was happening in some of the major manufactures
都想在做自己的HD摄像产品
is they were creating video level tools essentially HD tools
并试图将其推广到电影市场
and tried to push that into the cinema
不过我们所看到的是这些产品都差很远
and what we saw was that it’s not any close to good enough
我们想定一个很高的目标，那样才有意义
we want to set a high enough target so that was meaningful
这就是RED的本质
that’s the nature of RED
我们想把胶片送进养老院
we want to help to send the film to the retirement home
并用更好的来取代它
and have a few good about what took it place
2007年，RED 1面世
in 2007, the RED 1 was available to the public
在这个时代里，数位摄像机可以拍摄比HD更高的像素
this new generation, digital cameras could now shoot more resolution than HD
把像素数目从2K提高到4K
and increased pixels from 2k to 4k
当我看到RED的时候我想我真该给胶片打个电话：来认识下某人
when I saw the RED I really thought I should call the film on the phone and said: met someone
因为我认为这就是未来
cause I really thought this is the future
切格瓦拉，2008
无论分辨率、场景弧度还是看起来的感觉
the resolution, the curve, the way it saw like
都是全新的
I just felt this is a new thing
所以我坚持要用它来拍摄《切格瓦拉》
and I was insisted that we shoot CHE on it
数字技术在一开始很烂地球人都知道
digital at the beginning was really bad, everybody knew that
维尔莫斯 齐格蒙德，摄影
（猎鹿人/激流四勇士/花村）
这部比以前的要好
that kind of that camera which was better than previous ones
至少便宜，但是还是不够好
at least it was cheaper, ok, but it’s not good enough
因为总是有经验不足的问题
actually there is a experience limitation of that
它的确存在问题，它打压了小厂竞争，它是台电脑
(?)it has problems, it crushed occasion of the mob, it’s a computer
但是RED不顾胶片摄像机的尸体曾经怎样
but then again RED ignored everything about normal film camera bodies
转而使用自己觉得正确的东西
and use what they thought was right
最坏的情况也就是
even with the worst stories of being out
因为过热把所有东西上敷个冰袋
is that the heating had a ice pack on all that stuff
不过我不在乎
none of that bother me
因为得到的实在特别
because the get was so significant
很多天内都不用在100多度的情况下
in this case, not having to log film magazines up and down
用手把胶卷盒拿进拿出
this for days on hand in hundred degree
是不是能用闪存拍摄不重要
whether they are able to shoot on flash card
换存储盒只要50秒
change magazines in 50 seconds
这就已经是不错的冷却了
that alone was huge frost
也能让拍出的画面更好
it resulted in a better movie
*RED 1采用磁盘阵列或CF卡存储，相对胶卷和录像带拍摄时间大大延长*
我很喜欢吉姆詹那德这次的设计，我喜欢他们公司的理念
I really love the Jim Jannard’s doing, I love what their company’s about
我喜欢他们使用的技术，这不仅仅是
and I love the tech they took, that’s very much no holds barred like
“撸袖子大干一场爆眼球的什么东西”这样
let’s roll up our sleeves let’s get it in and up to our eyeballs, let’s figure this shit out
社交网络，2010
RED 1有9磅，加镜头14磅
RED 1 is 9 pounds when put up lens on it is 14 pounds
拍《社交网络》的时候很多时候要拍那些小船
on Social Network I went too many seconds I got to shoot these tiny boats
我觉得它们轻的就像薯片一样
and I think it’s like potato chips
所以我不能把30磅重的设备放到船顶的帆上
and I can’t add 30 pounds a camera out on this side sail top on this boat
然后他说：“好吧，你要我怎么做”
he said “ Ok what you want me to do”
我说：“你自己拿着，或者和别人搭伙
I said “you got to take one, you got to board out you got
不管怎样你要想出办法
whatever you got to do you have to figure out the way
给我个印第赛车版的RED 1”
you got to give me the indycar version of the RED 1”
*印第赛车是美国的方程式赛车，相对重量较轻*
这是在周五
this was on Friday
周日他就打电话给我说：
on Sunday, he called me and said:
“我用碳纤做了个机身，你什么时候来拿，就在我桌上”
“I made one of body in carbon fibers, when you can have about it, it’s on my desk”
然后用上的时候，这东西只有5磅半
and went down, and pick up to it and they were 5 and a half pounds
这在电影业中从未出现过
that never existed before for film cameras
这么快的回应
this sort of immediate calling responds
在电影制作人和摄像机制作人之间
between the people who are shooting and the people who are creating the cameras
贫民窟的百万富翁，2008
我迫切的想要制作点充满新鲜空气的东西
I was desperate to make something that had all the fresh air in
尤其是你去印度孟买的时候
and cause when you go to India in Bombay especially
鲜活的生命气息扑面而来，对你狂叫着
it’s got life, it’s just coming screaming on you all the time in everywhere
丹尼激动的产生了一个想法，我们应该在剧本中
Danny come to an idea, rage, come to an idea of speed energy use
用到速度和活力的元素
and that’s what we need on the script
跑，对，这就是我们要在印度用的
and then running, that’s it, that’s we use in India
那真是世界上最神奇的地方
it’s just the most wonderful place of the world
我们想要制作一部与众不同的电影，如果摄像机能实现那一点的话
for a different kind film we wanted the camera would trying somehow catch a bit of that
就是要找一部摄像机，任务明确了
it’s about finding camera, the task is there, it’s clear
我要做的就是用我狂妄自大又符合正统的经验去找到一件工具
my job is to find, with all my anarchic and conventional experience there, to find a tool
设备：矽映 SI-2K，2007
像矽映SI-2K这样的摄像机
cameras like Silicon Imaging SI-2K
可以到达对于胶片摄像机和早期
have been able to go places and get shots that
高清摄像机非常难以到达的地点进行拍摄
would have been very difficult with film or earlier versions of HD cameras
这里有个电脑传感器在后面
it’s a sensor of computer back on it
你想要把摄像机做的看起来像电脑一样吗
so do you make a computer look like a film camera?
或者你会把摄像机线拔掉，和笔记本连接在一起？
or do you say: “the hell of that, take this and ease that cable and connected into a laptop”
这就是SI摄像机的本事
and that will be the SI camera was
单凭这点世界上还没有如此之小的摄像机能够做到
at that point no one camera in the world is small enough
阿里 普莱斯勒，矽映总裁
安东尼想要在大街上追着孩子们跑
Anthony wanted to run into the streets and track the children as they were running
还得是和小孩一样的高度
and be as the same height level as the kids
所以他们把笔记本带上装包里
so they took macbook pros and put them into a bag pack
用作捕获和记录的系统
to use for their capture and recording system
胶片摄像机，就算从稳固架或起重机上卸下来
film cameras, even when off the legs or off the steadicam or off the crane
还是要和摄影者的身体连接在一起
still connected on the camera man’s body
他或者就这么追着你跑
he’s either chasing you down the street
或者把东西架在这然后转身带着那一大堆东西回来
or he’s got it here, or he turns round and runs back with things like that
不过用SI-2K就动能做到
with this SI-2K you can do that
因为它不再连着摄影者的身体了
it’s no longer connected to the camera man’s body
你能做好多其他的事
you can do different things with that
在片场可以真正做到“自由发挥”
during the scene it’s just literally improvising
2009年，《平民窟的百万富翁》获得了最佳摄影学院奖
in 2009, slum dog millionaire won the academic award for best cinematography
这是该奖项第一次颁发给几乎全程使用数字拍摄的电影
it was the first time that award was giving to a movie shot almost entirely on digital camera
所以既然您获得了学院奖
so you had the academic award
您觉得数字拍摄是否已经被主流接受了呢
so do you feel like that the film make digital be accepted by the main stream now?
《贫民窟》在评论界和观众当中的成功
the success of the slum dog with critics and audience
代表了一个时代的某些特点
symbolizes something of an époque
也算是为数字拍摄打定了基础
it perhaps puts hammers and stakes a little bit in the ground
这样看来数字格式已经被接受了
this far was acceptance of digital format
这是第一个对大规模使用数字技术的奖项
it was the first really acknowledgement on the large scale of digital
为此我非常为安东尼高兴
I was very pleased for Anthony for that
因为我以为他会觉得他永远也不能拿到这个奖
because I think he felt it was some acknowledgement he would never arrive at
因为他是如此特立独行于数码世界
because he’s chosen to specialized too much in the digital world
不过现在他的成就改变了所有人的看法
I think that was where he goes and everybody changed
公众之敌，2009
设备：SONY F23
第9区，2009
泰特罗，2009
设备：SONY F23
告密者，2009
设备：RED 1
阿凡达，2009
设备：SONY F950
《阿凡达》本来是我在《泰坦尼克号》之后的下一部电影
avatar was gonna be my next movie after titanic
所以在99年的时候我想把它拍成3D的
so I converted to think about it shoot in 3D in ‘99
我立刻就想到能在未来拍摄3D的唯一方法就是数字拍摄
I knew immediately that the only way to shoot 3D, the future of shooting 3D is digital
我们做了个实验，我们把2部高清摄影机并排放在一块
we’re starting to an experiment, we took 2 HD cameras side by side
我觉得结果还是相当酷的
I thought the result was pretty cool
接着我就和佩斯合作建立起了自己的摄像系统
then with Pace I built the vision camera system
一台摄像机放在这，另一台放到顶端
we’ve decided to put one camera here and another camera on top
那应该怎么整合这两个呢
so what happened in here to marry this two
因为从观测上说是需要两个画面的对吧？
cause there scopicly you need two images exist right?
没错
correct
我们有一个问题就是在摄像机较大的时候
one of the problems we have was the larger camera is a fact
我们不能像我们两眼位置一样把他们并排放置
that we wouldn’t put them side by side like your 2 eyeballs, right
文森 佩斯，卡佩3D技术CEO
你不能在现实世界把两架摄影机这么放
you couldn’t put those cameras physically in that position
他们会撞到的
they will run in to each other
所以我们利用镜面反射
so we use reflect of a mirror
这样在你的脑海里
and then that allows us to overlaid the 2 camera systems
两架摄影机的实际位置可以重叠
of your imagine form a physical stand point
而这样就不再有两眼间距离的限制
where there is no limitation how close we get these eyes together
而这一点对3D来说是非常重要的
and that’s really important to 3D
要制作3D效果
to create 3D
两架摄影机要像两只眼睛一样
2 cameras works a pair just like our 2 eyes
从稍微不同的角度获取画面
they capture pictures from slightly different angle
从而制造三维空间的深度和广度
providing the sense in 3 dimensional depth and distance
我有个圈内笑话
I have a joke of most people all around me
我属于平面世界
I long for when the world was flat
因为不止适应系统要互相复制
because it’s not only the cameras system duplicated
制作流程上的每件事都要相互复制
everything duplicates down the chain, right
一个镜头控制另一个镜头
so lensing control over lensing
很多人说这要加倍的难搞，实际上不对
and a lot people said that’s as twice as hard than that’s incorrect statement
不止是这样
that’s more than that
因为两架摄影机要像完全分不出来的双胞胎那样工作
because these 2 cameras have to operate like sign-missed twins
他们必须完美的复制对方
they have to mimic each other perfectly
如果电影制作完成一切正常的话
I think when films are done right and when it really works is when
你会觉得身临其境，自己就在那个旅程之中，完全沉浸于故事里
you feels I’m there, I’m in this journey and immerged the story line
对我来说最有趣的地方在于把这个工具交给真正的创造之手
the fun part for me is to really get this tools in the creative hands
这样就有人带你去你从未想象过的地方了
so people can really take you to place that you never imagine before
《阿凡达》出来的时候我真的很骄傲于它的画面，太棒了
Avatar came out and I was really proud of those images, look gorgeous
紧接着《爱丽丝梦游仙境》和《驯龙高手》也上映了
and it was followed up by Alice to wonderland and how to train your dragon
邦邦邦，市场上接二连三出现了3部3D电影
boo boo boo, 3 movies on the markets one after another and all of them were (?)
而且都是年度票房大户
the 3 of them were the top grossing films of the year
所以突然间大门敞开了
so all of a sudden the door just blow wide open on the whole thing
人们看到了这里的市场前景
people really saw the potential of this as a market
电影消费提升了观众
this consumptions of films has increased our audiences
的观影品味和理解能力
both appetite for them and now knowledge of them
所以想要制作惊人之作越来越难了
so therefore it’s getting harder and harder to impress
这就是3D为什么这么流行的原因之一
it’s one of the reasons why 3D’s taking off
换个口味看电影而已
just a way looking at a film
演员如同一尊雕塑，就是会走会动呼之欲出
the actor is like a sculpture or something only it’s moving and comes out
就像从剧院到电影，从无声到有声之类的一样
and like a combination when theater went film, music and everything
我恨3D，我带上了眼镜会觉得反胃
I hate 3D, I put on those glasses and I get sick in my stomach
黑的什么也看不清
it’s too dark looking through them
整个的3D现象实际上就是他妈的市场炒作难道不是吗？
the whole 3D phenomenon is a marketing fucking scheme isn’t it?
作为一个旁观者我可以肯定的说
I can safely say as a viewer
我完全不感兴趣
I’m totally uninterested in it
丁点兴趣也没有
I’m without any interests whatsoever
我觉得这就是一时火爆
I think it’s a fad
早晚烧个精光
I think it will burn out
电影工作室把什么都做成3D是不明智的
the studio’s not wise to slap 3D on everything
《阿凡达》之所以做成3D是有原因的
with Avatar there is a reason this movie is in 3D
它要给你一种体验
because it’s taking you on an experience
不是为了赚钱、哗众取宠或者玩把戏
it isn’t something that was on for money or a joke or a gimmick
因为它是被创作成那个样子的
it’s there because it was created that way
《阿凡达》结合了两种完全不同的电影制作方式
Avatar is 2 completed different forms of film making combine
我们只实际拍摄了1/3的内容
we only use lenses for about 1/3 of the movement
都是普通的东西
it all sets in just normal stuff
灯光，布景，拍5场
(?)lighting, mural, 5 action
其余的2/3是特效
it was virtual FX to the other 2/3
我们从来没去真的丛林，我们创造了一个丛林
we never shot a real jungle, we have create a jungle
都是建模
it’s all peer modeling
每个草叶每只蹦来蹦去的虫子
every blade of grass, every bug bouncing around
没有一个是真实丛林的场景
not one foot film shot in a real jungle
数学建模能完美创造真实世界
you have this idea that you could hold a mathematically perfect model for creating reality
只要计算机和软件就好
you just threw on the computing power at it, you just put software on it
我们就是这么干的，我们要求
cause it’s all we found, we required
艺术家和摄影师研究光在物体上如何反射
artist and people who trained in photography looking at how light interact with those things
然后以此为基础写代码，创造一个看起来很逼真的世界
to figure out how to write the code, to make it look real
数字操控带给眼睛的幻觉
what I find was that the manipulations the digital made your eyes to do
的确很引人入胜但却很空洞
they are all seductive but alternately a little bit hollow
我常用的一个比喻是我想起有个夏天
the analogy I used t use was I remember the summer when
玉米油可以让巧克力饼干很软
chips oil give these chocolate cookies (?) soft
这很不错啊，让饼干变软
that’s amazing, just soft cookie and
不过几个月过后
and then after a couple of months
在上面的完全是一坨化学XX
what’s on it is some horrible chemical crap
开始只是给了你美好的幻想
give you bad illusion it fooled you first
我所担心的是现在大规模使用CGI
my concern is that the image alternately with CGI
我们的年轻人也许不会再相信电影荧幕上的任何东西了
I don’t know the younger generation is believing anything anymore on screen
都不是真实的
it’s not real
你呈现了一个感觉真实却完全不是真实的世界
you are presenting complete unreality and make them feel like it was real
甚至都先于拍摄任何真实场景…
and before it was captured in reality…
好吧，你也进过不少片场吧
alright, you’ve been on a couple of movie sets
真实过吗
when was it ever real?
一堵墙，什么也没有
there was a kind of wall, there is nothing over there
30个人忙忙碌碌
there were 30 people stand around
一个拿着麦克风，一个在梯子上的人把屁股沟露出来了(=  =)
a guy with a boom mic, the other guy upon a ladder with his ass crack hanging out
还有个起重机，纽约的夜晚可能是伯班克的白天
there is a sit crane, your street night exterior New York was a day exterior Burbank
哪里真实了？
what was it ever real
极速赛车手，2008
在老的拍摄技法中我们更为灵活
we are free of the old technology of capturing images
摄像机，胶片，镜头，曝光
camera, film, lens, exposure
我能掌控很多，有更多选择，更多点子
it give me more control, more choice, more wits
去达成脑中的想象
to access what you are imagining in your head
哈利波特与混血王子，2009
特效分解
电脑技术只能越来越好
computers will only get better and better
你能够把任何东西创造的足够真实
will be able to produce anything you want completely realistic
而且换个想法，如果时间足够，你也可以融入到那个世界
and alternately, if you got enough time, the world is all yours there
双塔奇兵，2003
斯巴达三百勇士，2006
加勒比海盗：世界尽头，2007
守望者，2009
你要抓紧学习抓住自己的想象
you have to try to outpace study and seize your imagination
做出人们从没见过的东西，而这样的东西一年比一年更真实
do something they haven’t seen before and every year it getting more and more real
诸神之怒，2010
特效分解
艺术家和电影制作者在不断提升画面的内涵、视觉效果和真实性
the artiest and the film maker are constantly trying to up the immanence spectacle and realism
所以现在的情况是从来没出现过的
so that really put this in a positions of like never before
同时拓宽了艺术和技术
really having to wide technology and art
数字技术真的很厉害
that was great about the digital technology
一两年内就可能再上一个新台阶
it should doubled in everything in one or two years
你想做什么只要想好
once you set your mind on that path
一切变的容易，不过是时间的问题
it all becomes very simple, it just be a matter of time
因为数字技术在不断进步
cause digital is gonna continue to improve
摄像机公司像RED，阿莱，索尼和其他的
camera companys like RED, ARRI, SONY and others
在不断改进自己的商品
are constantly developing new products continue to make advances
让它们在动态范围、分辨率和颜色上有更好表现
on dynamic range, resolution and color
我喜欢看这些厂商竞争
I love that all these manufactures are competing against each other
把大摄像机做的更小，更快，更便宜，传感更好
to make big cameras smaller, faster and cheaper, better sensored
最近数位摄像机的
with dynamic range of digital camera
动态范围卡在10档
up until recently have been limited to really match to 10 stop
设备：RED EPIC
不过在EPIC或ALEXA上你不用担心这个问题
but you don’t see that problem in the EPIC or the ALEXA
设备：阿莱 ALEXA
数位摄像机的动态范围已经比原来好多了
the dynamic range was much better when I was use to with digital
90年代中期的时候，阿莱生产的还全是化学照相摄像机
up untill the mid-90s, for ARRI, it was all photo chemical
格伦 康奈，阿莱首席技师
当我觉得数字技术已经成熟
we solve the digital technology mature to a point that were
我们也开始发展自己的数字摄像机
we began and invite the digital technology
我们用在ALEXA上的传感器
the sensor that we used now on the ALEXA camara
设备：阿莱 ALEXA，2010
让我们骄傲的说，其拍摄质量足以制作电影正片
allowed us to offer a camera that we can proudly promote as a feature film camera
ALEXA拥有所有令我们兴奋的元素
the ALEXA takes all of that we are excited about
在电影制作中可以带来胶片具有的质感
in film making and brings those textural qualities that film has
及熟悉的色彩表现
brings that definitely familiar color space
最近我才对ALEXA感兴趣，因为他是阿莱的新产品
and only recently I’m realy interested in ALEXA made by Arriflex not heard
而且和用胶片拍摄没什么不同
that it’s like shooting film with digital format
非要我使用数字拍摄的话
if I’m push to shoot on digital
我会用ALEXA，因为可以得到很好的效果
I will take the ALEXA and that could help me get good result
雨果，2011
设备：阿莱ALEXA
亡命驾驶，2011
忧郁症，2011
设备：阿莱ALEXA
时间规划局，2011
这是RED的新产品，我们叫它EPIC
this is the new RED, we just call it EPIC, so
信不信由你，可是比RED 1提高了60%的像素
this is, believe it or not, 60% more resolution than the RED 1
吉姆詹那德给我看他的新产品EPIC
when Jim Jannard showed me the EPIC
我看着它说：“等等，
I looked at it and I said: “ wait a minute
“这个能干什么？
“what did that do?
“能怎么帮助你将故事？”
“how could that free you as a story teller”
龙纹身的女孩，2011
设备：RED EPIC
超凡蜘蛛侠，2012
它能拍摄非常美丽、丰富、
this camera created those beautiful, rich,
自然或者说格调独特的颜色
very natural or very stylisticly wonderful colors
霍比特人，2012
设备：RED EPIC
我们要用分辨率4K的放映机在超大屏幕上放映
we’ve taken a digitally projective 4k images on a gigantic screen
那效果一定震人心魄
and it is absolutely mind-blowing
影院的运输方式要改变了
the delivery system of cinema is going to change
这比摄影机本身更令我兴奋
and that’s actually more exciting a way for me beside the actual camera
因为那种老掉牙的一套：
cause the ancient system of
送电影上卡车，到不同的城市，再卸货
film on a truck driving into a city and unloading it
要被取代了
that being replaced
运送巨大的胶卷铁盒子到处跑是相当费钱的
the old way of having ship giant film case around is very very expensive
所以人们意识到如果使用数字放映
so the business realized that there was a tremendous possible savings
可以省一大笔钱
in digital delivery and digital projection
我们都想要母片，底片的第一版
we are all want the pristine print, first print of all the negative
不过这不可能
but we cannot have that
你必须拷贝
so you have to copy it
但是用数字放映就没必要拷贝了
and the advance of DCP is not real copying
扫描完成后不需要复印
once it scanned, it doesn’t get copied again
更像是克隆，完全一样的东西
it’s cloned, so it’s exactly the same thing
我对数字放映机更有好感
I’m getting more impressed with digital projection
我不是技术帝
as much as…I’m not big on technology
但我觉得数字放映机的发展前景是极好的
I think digital projections will come a long way
过去的两年我们卖了10000台数字放映机到影院
in the last 2 years we’ve sold 10,000 digital projectors into cinemas
全球都在换
the conversion is taking place globally
现在我们已经完成了50%
we were probably 50% or more there
剩下的很快就会完成
and the rest of the conversion will happen very quickly
既然令人惊叹的电影已经制作出来
they produce gorgeous pictures
那么我们就必须创造更好的表现方式
and you had to study building up a wave
所以我们要让数字屏幕在2015年达到200000块
that’s why we’re gonna up to 200,000 digital screens by 2015
传统的印片方式岌岌可危
the model for printing film is endangered
但我不希望最终胶片也是这样
and ultimately I hope that it doesn’t take film with it
小时候去看电影
as a kid, I went to the movies
坐下后看到红色的幕帘
you sat down and looked at a big red curtain
接着幕帘拉开
and then that curtain parted
电影就开始了
and there is the movie was going to begin right?
巴瑞 莱文森，导演
（恐怖海湾/少年福尔摩斯/雨人）
然后你惊呼：“天啊，真带劲儿！”
and you went “oh, my gosh! oh, this is special!”
这是我童年时代的印象
that’s my childhood image
如今这已经不是带劲儿的事了
it’s not special anymore
已经是别的了
it’s another thing
一个世纪以来电影院都跟教堂似的
in a way cinema was a church between a century
因为同样是很多人进到一个又大又黑的房间
because we come to this large dark room and sit
看着屏幕想这会是个什么故事
looked up and think what it would tell you
卡萨布兰卡，1942
好多关于穿衣、行为、怎么讨好姑娘和怎么扮演英雄
enormous amount how to dress how to act be with woman how to act hero
那个时代的屏幕很不同
something is extraordinary about the scene
有40尺高
at that age is 40 feet high
那么大一块屏幕
and in 40 feet high,
相对日常生活很多事都变得神奇起来
something mythic about it is beyond your everyday life
跨度也很广，应该有80尺
it’s so much big huge span, it should be 80 feet wide
观众应该被屏幕包围
you should envelop the audience in the screen
因为那才是电影院- -对，那才是电影院
cause that’s cinema--yeah, that’s cinema
声音也每时每刻包围着你
and the sound around you every minute
我真是不明白为什么有人喜欢在电脑上看电影
I mean why people want to watch movies on their computers I should never know
我经常在地铁上看到有人用iPhone看电影，人后我就想…
I see people watch movies on their iphone in subway all the time…
“不要啊！！”
and I went “---no!!!”
有人说这不是好事，不过也不一定非有那么糟
who might say this is bad, it doesn’t have to be bad
晚上我妻子睡了，我睡不着
late at night, my wife sleeps and I can’t sleep
我就会拿起我的iPhone
and I put my xx on my iphone
再带上副不错的耳机，把屏幕几乎贴脸的看电影
put up good headphone and watch films close to my face
这很有趣
and this sound interesting about that
一切都很私人
you‘ve got everything very privately
所以挺怀念想哭的却不想人看见的时候
I think it was missing I want to cry without people seeing it
我放《钢铁木兰花》的时候哭了
I want to cry without people seeing it, I’ll put the steel Magnolias
要是我妻子醒了，我只好暂停，再藏到枕头里
and I cry and if my wife wakes up I just get pause and put it under a pillow
这很有趣
and get something interesting about that
因为以前不可能有机会经历
because you didn’t have a chance to experience before
莱娜 杜汉，演员/导演
（微型家具）
约会已经不会有人问“去看电影吧”
You can ask on a date no body’s like “let’s get on the movies” any more
甚至现在已经是这样的
I don’t even felt that’s going on, I felt like
人们会说“我们在床上看看Netflix有什么吧”
people like “let’s watch something on Netflix streaming on my bed” which
*Netflix：相当于掌上影院*
然后一群24岁的年轻人就在床上等着
was 24 years old guys waiting to get you sit on their bed
不过这确实是正在发生的事情
but I think that’s what’s happening
我能看到正在上映的电影，能从平板电脑或其他的什么上看任何电影
I can get any on movie I can get any movie from pad or anything
对我来说再自然不过，坐下就看呗
That’s naturalest thing to me I can sit down and watching
不过会丢掉好多细节啊，那就没法感受电影的魅力了
but you will not see all the detail that you won’t be able to feel it
比如说就没法感受…
like if you be able to feel…
我的高清电视大着呢
my big HDTV is 20 big
你是说和女孩子亲热这类的东西吗？
You mean go to see make up with girls like that
没兴趣，我早过了那个年龄了
But that, no, I’m way past that
真的吗？
Are you sure?
相信我啦
Believe me
看电影的方式越来越多
So many different way for watching movie
分享经历的方式
That sharing experience aspect to it
正在改变看去影院看电影的习惯
That shifting, going to the movies
也很大程度上变得虚拟了
Well it’s also becoming much larger virtually
可视世界已经大大像虚拟化延伸了
Mural space was definitely spanned virtually
大家在虚拟世界里分享电影
So they’re watching movies together in this sort of virtual worlds
几乎是不可避免的
And that will be inevitable
费洛蒙也要虚拟交换么？
You had to get the Pheromone to exchange virtually
（啥？）怎么流血怎么流汗，不接触怎么爽啊
(Yeah?) how do you bleed and sweat and be comfortable without getting together
你在影院做那些吗？穿着拉风风衣？
You do that in the theater? In your trench coat
倒没有，不过可以一起笑一起哭啊
No but laughing together and crying together
有时候虚拟的经验反而更加奏效
Some way the virtual experience is more rewarding because
因为总有实际的对话框在
There is a actual dialog going on
这些20多岁的小年轻不在乎
So these 20-year-old does not care
不过在共享空间倒有很多影院呢
But there are lots of cinemas in the communal space
他们只谈论在脸书还是什么上又交了什么好友
There they just sit in and tell a story getting friends on Facebook or whatever it is
你得适应，你要适应不了也没事
You got to go with it, if you can’t be able to deal with it
因为你的时代已经过去了
that’s fine, because it means your time is finished
大家看开点吧
it’s time for all the people to take it on
30以下的小孩们
the kids, 30 and under
在电脑电视上看了无数的数字影像
have seen endless digital image on their computer, on their television
对于他们，那就是他们的电影
and that to them is their film
我曾经希望这些小型摄像机
I just had hoped that these little cameras
可以促成民间电影的一场革命
will make a revolution where you would say the folk films good
不过自己制作的话
Just do it ourselves
许多才华和人才都因为免费而得不到足够尊重
so a lot of talent and stuff could be free by less respect
全民都在解读电影
Everyone is interpreting
他们通过镜头和画面解读事实或者自以为的事实
Their reality or what they did their reality through an image, through a lens
不过有些孩子真的还挺擅长这个的
And some kids are really good at it, I’ll tell you
微型家具，2010
设备：佳能 7D
我热爱DV文化，否则我也不会拍这部电影
I love digital video culture, or I won’t never making with this
因为我是作家出身，而我认为
Because I came out as a writer and I thought that as
电影制作人应该是有专业知识
you have certain kind of knowledg
然后可以自由操控
and basically my head keeps a thought like a dude
拍摄机器的那么一个人
who operational machine to do this job
我觉得真踏上那条路我会害怕的
I think I would be scared to step into that road
巨大的摄像机和15人的灯光团队
If it had to involve getting a huge camera and get a 15 lightening technicians together
我觉得用这样小而且私人的方式体验电影制作就可以了
I was able to experience making movies small private way which I need to do
佳能5D和尼康单反如何呢
What about the 5Ds, what about the DLSRs
这些相机是给记者设计的
These cameras are designed to the request of APM writers
摄影师可以拍摄新闻视频给网站
So there news photographers could shoot news video for their websites
仅此而已
That’s it
人们会觉得
then people came along went:
“哇，还不错，我也要用”
“woo, I like the look of that, I’m gonna use that”
然后效果也不错
And it can work
不过拍电影可不行 --  为什么？
but I hate it being used as movie cameras -- Why?
不够好
It’s not good enough
但是它们便宜，人人都能拍电影
But they ain’t expensive, people can make movies
如果我是艺校的学生，有台7D或5D
If I’ve been in art school and I have a Canon 7D or 5D
那肯定很棒
It would be wonderful
你今晚用什么拍？
What are you shooting on tonight?
7D。天，7D耶
-7D. Oh my God, that’s 7D
是为了研二的作业
For my second year of grad film
我猜是因为易用，拍的不赖，而且不贵
I guess it’s accessible, give you a lot that you can capture, but it’s not super expensive
舒提 甘古利，纽约大学研究生
我用7D或5D拍摄主要是预算原因
I want to shoot with the 7D or 5D primarily for budget reasons
还因为只有一周时间可用了
And because we are given a week in which we have to shoot our film
大部分时间都花在了选题、约场地
And in amount of time we were lose in terms like changing film checking the gate
所以时间不够用也是原因
And then I would probably not be able to film the soon I want to
想要讲自己的故事变得很便宜
It becomes the very cheap way for us to tell our stories about ourselves
它已经跳出了与环境抗争的艺术载体
It takes this art format out of where fighting environment
很多人都加入了艺术创作的行列
and a lot more people to make art
人人都有纸和笔
Everybody and his little brother has a piece of paper and pencil
但伟大的故事又
But how many great stories had been written
在这纸上写出多少呢
on that piece of paper
现在同样的事要发生在电影身上了
Now the same thing is gonna happen in cinema
几个电影人聚在一起
There used to be in conference when film making guys
坐在咖啡店闲谈
people sat in coffee shop and saying
说如果有机会，自己会制作多么伟大的电影
What great film they would make if the man would ever give me a chance
现在好了，人人有机会，放手去做就行
It was kind of great when the day came that it was we go do it
现在每个人都能做电影，电影遍地开花，这不错
Everybody can make a movie now, movies are everywhere, that’s a good thing
我不这么认为，其实好处少
I don’t think so actually, there’s less good
坏处多
There’s more bad
因为每个人都想做什么做什么
because everybody is able to do whatever they want to do
真是民主，真是不错
That’s democratization out there, that’s fantastic
但是我们的下一代会吃苦头的
But I think my kids will suffer
他们再不会享受到我们成长时期所拥有的品质了
they will not have the qualities we have been growing up
因为不会再有人…
Cause there isn’t somebody there…
不会再有人在乎品味了
There isn’t a taste make involved
天
Wow!
胶片已经完了么？您怎么看
Is this the end of film? What do you think?
我觉得，赛璐珞仍然是个选择
I think celluloid is still gonna be a choice
大艺术家，2011，胶片摄制
点球成金，2011，胶片摄制
碟中谍：幽灵协议，2011，胶片摄制
生命之树，2011，胶片摄制
战马，2011，胶片摄制
饥饿游戏，2012，胶片摄制
黑暗骑士崛起，2012，胶片摄制
转变只因为有一个新的选择
a transition starts with people offering a new choice
不过是否意味着旧的选择即将被取代
But if it finished it will take the old choice away
我不认为现在的技术已经准备好了
I don’t think techniques are ready to do that yet
我们有100多年纯粹用胶片拍摄的历史
we have hundred years of experience basically shooting on film
而现在胶片也还在使用
And film it still around
不管乔治卢卡斯说什么“胶片已死”
No matter what George Lucas said that “film is dead”
他其实20年前就这么说了
he said that 20 years ago
但是胶片没有死，人们还是喜欢用胶片
But film is not dead because people like to shooting on film
因为胶片真的可以呈现难以置信的美
because it really has an incredibly beautiful look
谁在乎啊
Who cares
20年内他们就不会再说胶片怎样怎样
In 20 years from now they wouldn’t be saying what looks like film
转而说“看看我的数位摄像机能做什么吧”
they would be saying “look what I can do with my digital”
我会是最后还在使用胶片摄像的人
I will be the one last guy shooting film
因为没人剩下了
Cause no one else would be left shooting film
而且我确定在10年间我也会开始使用数字技术
But I certain will be use digital technology within the next 10 years
我希望，要是5到10年内胶片还存在的话
I hope, if in another 5 or 10 years film still exists
我还是打算继续用胶片拍
I still plan to shoot on film
胶片是不是完了？
Is it the end of film?
对，我猜它是完了
Yeah, I guess it is
而且我认为5年之内，胶片就会
And I think in 5 years, film will be
胶片就几乎不会存在了
film will be exception, I really do
胶片设备销售在2007年达到了顶峰
Film production peaked in 2007
比尔 罗素，阿莱摄像部副总裁
我们在那时已经是10%过盛生产胶片摄像机了
Our factory at that time was working 110% to produce film cameras
然后呢
Then what happened?
然后世界变了
Then the world changed
所有的订单都变成数字的了
New purchases are all digital
胶片摄影机可以延续数十年
Film cameras can last for decades
仍能使用也仍被使用
They will be still available and in use
然而，主流厂商
However, our major manufactures
已经停止新胶片摄像机的发展
have seized the development of new film cameras
“结束了，阿莱、潘纳维申的胶片摄像机”
“电影摄像机公司已静静停止生产胶片摄像机”
他们不再生产胶片摄影机了
They no longer make them
我们不得不和赛璐珞说再见了
We will have to say goodbye to celluloid
胶片会消失
it will go away I’m afraid
“胶片像影机，1888-2011”
因为某些特殊用途它们还是会存在
And they will be cared for special occasions
但是其它的都要变了
I think, but it’s gonna change
一旦这个选择消失了
once that option is gone
嗯
Right
一旦现在的年轻人不再有胶片电影的体验
Once young people don’t have the experience
我觉得我们正在经历这场全面变革
I think we are living through this total transformation
我觉得大概人们都会担心这会是没完没了的吵杂
I think in general people will fear it’s just endless noise
没人说的清什么是好的，什么是坏的
no one was able to tell what’s good or bad
没人能真正做出好东西
No one will be able to make good things
所有好的都会消失
And good things will just get lost
我觉得我们的文化继承岌岌可危
That in danger I think, the continuation of our culture
一切归于尘土
What will back to me need to back to the wild
嗯
Right
你从哪里获得文化、艺术和知识的给养呢
Where did you get the nourishment of culturally, artistically, intellectually
哪里呢
Where did you get it
电影制作的关键一步是存档
And an important step of movie making process is archival
把成片和其他材料储存起来
Storing the final complete movie and materials used to create it
没人把存档当回事
Nobody takes archival seriously
人们都把东西存在硬盘里
They’re all save it on hard drive
放了一年再拿出来
And if the hard drive on the shelf and a year later
放的时候可能就出现“哒哒哒”的声音
You load it, it just got “ter…ter…”
因为卡住了
Because they stick
它不会总是这样
You don’t find them all time they stick
不过要是你发现了
If You do find out all the time
那就是坏了，然后哒哒响
they wear out and go “ter…ter…”
1950年代起，在电视广告开始兴盛的时期
Since the early 1950s, since the advance of the commercial television
迈克尔 五井，摄影，美国摄影师协会主席
有80多种视频格式
There had been 80 formats of video
现在这80多种视频格式
Today, these 80 formats of video
的大多数已经完全不能播放了
most cannot be played anymore
就因为播放器已经不存在了
Cause the machine simply don’t exist
拍电影的时候我们会把样片做2个数字备份
When we make a movie we have 2 digital copies of all of the dailys
你把这些拷贝装箱的时候
When you box those how to be stored
最好放个播放器在旁边
Yet put a reader in with that thing
我有8种80年代做的音乐短片和广告存档格式
I have archival 8 formats for music video and commercials I did n 1980s
已经没机器能播了
And there’s no machine that can play them
在数字世界你完全找不到
There are no archives or formats or anything
任何实体存档格式
in the digital world that you will put any stock in
所以数字格式的存档问题含待解决
so their archive issues are simply not being dealt with yet
对于电影
The only thing you can sure of the on film
或其他的动态影像来说
or anything of the moving image
你能保证存储个六七十年的
is gonna be around may by for 60 or 70 years from now
很有趣也很讽刺
Interestingly enough, ironically enough
只有赛璐珞
The celluloid
盖瑞 因豪斯，柯达首席技术官
胶片是特别的
Film is unique
因为胶片同时是捕获和存储介质
Because film is a capture medium and an storage medium
所以你要回看的话
So if you really want to go back
只要保存得当
and if you can restore it in the right conditions
100年后只要有光
A hundred years later all you have to do is shining light through it
也还是可以看
And you are able to see it
不会有格式淘汰的问题
There were never be format obsolete
爱德 斯塔拉德曼，动态影像助理馆长
乔治 伊斯特曼博物馆（世界最古老的摄影博物馆和影片藏馆）
1909年
There was a conference in 1909
胶片的规格和标准被整理确定
Where they put together the standard for film
102年未变
While it hasn’t changed for 102 years
我用氮气保存的胶片
I have a film in my nitrogen forms
现在仍能在放映机上放映
I can pull it out and run it on the projector today
尽管我知道这是1895年拍摄完成的
even know it was made in 1895
如果换个观点，想想存档
If the point, alternately the archiving is
可以是原始作品的完全复制
the faithful reproduction of the original product
那电影人现在有更好的机会
Film makers now have a better chance
让自己的作品可以
of something I may being showed properly 50 years from now
在50年后仍完美展现
that I ever have in history
可人们总说“我们可不知道50年后会发生什么
people keep saying “we don’t know what’s going to happen in 50 years,
“也许就没法播放了
“we don’t know how to read the information or
“也许就烂掉了，你必须转换它要不就没有了”
“it’s going to decay, you have to migrated or it will die”
对，没错，得转换，不过还有一件事
yeah, sure, you will, and some of the those things are true
这样的解决方案总比胶片好
all of them are better scenario than film
几乎这世界上的所有东西
all of everything in this whole world
都在用数字存储
is stored digitally
是啊
yeah
对啊，问题就在这里
Yeah, there are problems with it
但是问题是可以被解决的
But they are gonna solve those problems
这点我保证
I’ll guarantee that
这么多的数字信息
There’s too much digital information out there
不可能没有更全面的存储解决办法
not to figure out a full proof way to storage forever
历史总是在进步
Archeology always improves
某些我们无法控制的变化
So as the way we lose things change
也许正是我们找到解决方案的契机
The way that we invent to find them changes
所以您并不担心这些消失的东西咯
So you are not worried about all these disappearing
如果某件事对人类真的是重要的
Is things are important for human beings
那就肯定会有保存的办法
we figure out a way to preserve them
这总是没错的
It’s always been truth
这是我们生活的一部分
Yes we do that part of life
有一天我们也许会在舞台上展示胶片印片
We might get to the stage where a print of a film
因为稀有而使它更像一件艺术品
Is so rare is almost like an art object
而我们可以说：
And we can go back and say
“这是一份胶片的印片，全世界唯一一份”
“this is actually a print of film and it’s the only one of the world.”
一两百年后这些都不会剩下任何踪迹
100, 200 years from now there won’t be a trace of this left
我们现在所制造的东西也都没有任何踪迹
And there won’t be trace of anything we make now
所以你身在何方？能把你怎样
So where are we? what fucked you?
我从不相信
I don’t believe in one second that
数字影片或数字技术
digital imaging or digital technology
会改变人类讲故事的方式
will ever take the way the humanity of story-telling
2001太空漫游，1968
因为这关于我们的本质
beause story-telling in it on ourselves
这是神圣的人类事物
it’s a holy human concern
艺术家比较淳朴，科学家也比较淳朴
artist primordial, science also quite primordial
这其实很和谐
so kind of all these things are very harmony things
他们总是在互相推进
They always had to push on one another
我们已经达到化学摄像技术的顶端
We are at the top of photo chemical process
也就能走这么远了
This is about far as we’re ever gonna go
但是用数字技术的话，我们就重新回归到初始了
When you are using digital, you are at the very bottom again
所以要跳出传统帮助创新
So you should jump over and help to build that
因为越多人使用才能使这项技术越好
Cause more people use it, the better it gets
除非你参与到这场变革中
Unless you are participate into the revolution
否则就会被落下
Or you will be lost in past
我们不能说“没我的事
We can’t call ourselves as “we don’t care
看你们了”
They are up to your guys now”
我们要参与其中
So we have to be in it
每个人都能参与到这个过程中
Everyone will have access to both the means of the production
也能立刻了解到曾经发生的事
and watch everything ever exist instantly
随着数字技术持续改变我们讲故事的本质
As digital continues to change the nature of story-telling
我们也在改变
We also continue to change
甚至这种改变我自己都不能理解
In ways that I could not even understand
不过所有的都在改变，这就成了一场巨大的变革
But all things do that and it becomes a giant revolution
人们喜欢好故事，好故事能带他们去从未体验过的世界
People love great stories, they let them getting into the world they haven’t experienced
至于是怎么去的，我觉得并不重要
And how they get there, it doesn’t really matter
我们开始使用数字技术到如今的程度，并不意味着停滞不前了
One shouldn’t even think we stop when now we reach digital this is it
完全不是，想想看娱乐形式如何表现
No, no, think about where the entertainment imports
大众需求又何去何从
Where the need is going to go
您能感觉到技术上您所在的位置吗？
Do you feel technologically with where you are
您是否觉得自由？
Dou you feel free
我不认为我想要去感觉
I’m not sure that I ever want to feel
我们已经到达了某处，从技术上讲
that we arrived, technologically
我觉得我们总能做得更好
I always feel that there is something we can do better
我们的前辈给了世界去梦想的新时代
The people who coming to us gave the world new ace to dream
我认为我们要继续他们的事业
I think it’s our job to continue that
继续给人们创造梦想
and to try to give people new ace to dream
所有最后都会回归到一件事
Everything comes down to one thing
如果你用心去做
If you do something with your heart
如果你能够让我们感受到它
if you do something convince us to feel about it
那你用什么做到的并不重要
It doesn’t matter what you using